He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by
God and experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of
Spirits. Hey everybody, it's March 14th. Some people call it Pi Day but if you know
how to pronounce that letter in Greek it's very different. So good evening to
giant killers. You can't you can't segue over into eating Pi if you pronounce it
the other way. That's correct. What is it going to consume if you pronounce it the
right see that
That's why it's a problem.
That's why I think you're making it a problem.
Sans pedantry there is no issue here.
That's all right.
Right.
Yes.
What podcast is this?
That's right.
It's the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host Father Stephen the Young is with me from Lafayette Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymak,
and Emeas Pennsylvania.
And we are live.
And if you're listening to us live and not
listening to the recording. You can call us at 855-237-2346, just like the voice of Steve just said.
We're going to get your calls in the second half of the show and Elijah is going to be taking your
calls. And he's a little out of control. He already did that little record scratch thing at the
beginning of the intro. So who knows what's going to happen when he comes back? It could be a crazy
night. So yeah, yeah. So we've talked about the Torah probably in just about every
episode of the podcast. And here we are now at episode number 87. How many
thousands of hours is this podcast now? I've lost, lost count. Until now, though,
we have not discussed the Torah in any focused and overarching way to talk about
the Torah as the Torah. So what are the questions that we often get? And that
frankly is often raised in Christianity. Is this what is the relationship of the
old testament, especially the Torah to the New Testament.
what exactly did Christ mean when He said He came not to abolish the Torah but to fulfill it.
And what does that fulfillment look like?
So, level with me, Father, when Jesus said that He did not come to abolish the law but to fulfill it,
He basically meant that He was abolishing it, right?
I mean no kosher, am I right?
No.
See, the thing is, you didn't even know which part of that He's taking down to.
Yes, thank you.
A lot of day.
No, there is no kosher or no, he's not right or no.
No, you do still have to worry about how your pickles were killed.
It's not the killing of the pickle is not ritualized.
You especially don't want to eat a dill pickle with its blood still in it.
You want to make sure it's kosher, Dill.
Yeah.
Yeah, I mean that I don't want to go too far down this rabbit trail but is
is
Is the Vlasic Pickle Stork Jewish?
Is that what we're being led to believe?
If so, if so, he is almost certainly a litfac because the Stork is the national animal
of Lithuania.
See it all comes back around.
I played right into it.
That's right.
Actually, around this time of year is when the Stork start coming back, so it's very timely.
It's like the swallow is coming back to Capastrana.
So, yeah, we talk about the Torah a lot.
We've said a lot of things about the Torah.
We've even at least addressed the whole idea
of abolishment versus fulfillment of the Torah
before, at least in brief.
Yeah.
But beyond those summary statements, as you alluded to,
there's a question of what that looks like,
and getting more into specifics.
So with tonight and next week's show and who knows what else we're going to be sort of
two weeks.
Don't get people excited we're having a show next week.
No, a couple of weeks.
A couple of weeks.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, they notice when we say these things, you know, and then they get crazy when we don't
do what they have.
Well, so I didn't say next week's show was going to be Lord of Spirits.
No, okay.
Right.
Like, who knows what kind of shows I'm putting on here in Lafayette, right?
There you go.
None in the first week of length though, but with the next, yeah, with at least these
next few shows, we're going to be sort of gradually zooming down to very particulars,
right? Because it's one thing to say, for example, as I think I said, or something similar
in religion, the apostles, I don't go back and read my own books either. That would be really
weird. But um...
I said something in the last chapter along the lines of every commandment of the Torah
is still an effect in the Orthodox Church, something along those lines.
And it's one thing to say that, and it's even one thing to kind of make an argument where
people can kind of nod their head to that, but then, you know, so I can't eat an owl,
right?
when you get down to the
the like super I don't know why you want to eat an owl. I mean maybe an owl is all you got. But, you know,
but getting into the weeds right we're going to get a little more we're going to gradually getting to the weeds.
We're going to be we're going to start sort of zoomed out over the course of tonight. We're going to zoom closer and then in two weeks in a mere fortnight.
we will be zooming in even closer and getting into said hypothetical aforementioned weeds.
But for tonight, we're starting with the broader view, the more zoomed out. So we've talked
about before how the Torah is sort of the foundation stone of the
of scripture. That the Old Testament or the Hebrew Bible is the Torah plus
additional books. That's why it sometimes referred to as just the Torah and the
prophets or the Torah, the prophets and the writings. But the Torah, there is always
present. We've talked about a lot at various times from various
perspectives about how all the different Judaism's of the second temple period had
somewhat different can in some of them very expansive, some of them very restricted, but there was
one thing in common, all of them had the Torah. Yeah. Yeah. Even in... So we've even talked about how
there were certain groups that were deeply grounded in inachic Judaism.
So the book of Enic, the book of Jubilee's, and then the book of the Giants,
other related, anachic literature form, this sort of central, occupied this central place
to reserve their reading of scripture, places like Comeron, for example.
And involved with that, so involved with parts of the book of Enic, there is a sort of diminishment
of the import.
of Moses and even sort of a diminishment one could say of the Torah in a certain sense,
at least in the sense of certain of the commandments, but even in those places, for example in
cumeron. Yes, first enich and jubilee's are the second and third most common
text there but number one is Genesis.
which less we forget is part of the Torah.
Yeah. So, even the Nakhik Judaism, which in some ways was arrival to
Ferrisseic Judaism in the first century BC, in the first century AD,
and therefore kind of arrival to the way in which Ferrisseic Judaism
planted itself firmly in the commandments of the Torah.
It was still based and grew out of the Torah just with a very different reading and understanding of it.
So the Torah is at the core.
Everything else is added to the Torah in the Old Testament or the Hebrew Bible.
What we call the historical books or the former prophets are also called by scholars the Deuteronomistic History
because they describe
the history of Israel through a lens and in terms and based on principles that are outlined in the
book of Deuteronomy which is the Torah. Everything is based on Torah. When we get to the New Testament
we find that the structures of the New Testament can and parallel and mirror the Hebrew Bible or the
the Old Testament in that we have the Gospels.
which are presented in a certain way as a new Torah,
not as a new Torah that replaces the old Torah,
but as the interpretation of the Torah
directly related to the person of Jesus as the Messiah.
We tend to diminish in the gospels,
Jesus preaching we've been taught to do this.
by a Protestant culture, all of Christ preaching, all of his teaching, all of those kind of things
are sort of the run-up to his death and resurrection, right? Mainly his death, but then also, of course,
his resurrection. And you'll even see a lot of scholars point out, well, about one third of each
of the gospels is passionate, is death and resurrection. And that's an
outsize.
portion agreed, but the other two thirds is other stuff, right? Which is important. And when you
look at that other stuff, when you look at Christ's preaching and the parables, when you look at his
interactions with the Pharisees and the Sadducees and the Herodians and the scribes, in all of the
gospels of leading up parts, what they're talking about, what they're arguing about, what they're
fussing to him about what the issues are all surrounding the Torah and its interpretation.
They're all surrounding the Torah and its interpretation.
And when we get to the epistles in the New Testament, the epistles are taking the Hebrew
scriptures as read through the Gospels, not the literal text of the Gospels, but what
is presented in the Gospels in terms of the life of Jesus the Messiah and applying that,
getting it into application in the lives of the recipient.
of the different letters. So even the New Testament is fundamentally grounded in the Torah.
I would have argued that if you have the Torah as a Christian, you actually have all the basis
you need for Christian theology. Just in the Torah. It would be hard to test this thesis, but
My sense is that almost every error in theology is an error of either not knowing the Torah,
or as I think you've said before, believing that God is in some way not free,
or some combination of the two.
Yeah, you know that that that and I mean
Honestly, I think a lot of the ills of Christianity
in here in the 21st century come from not knowing
what is in the Torah.
It's a lot of it is actually really straightforward,
but we don't want it to be,
especially some of the stuff in the Vedic case, for instance.
Right, right.
And we, there are any number of reasons
why this is the case.
Right, and some of them express themselves as fairly
benign, right, like they'll want to embrace the fulfillment language and just say, well,
you know, the New Testament explains all that or, right, Jesus is the fulfillment of that.
So we could just read that. Right, there's a sense of, you know, now we've got this other text
that supersedes the first one. So it's nice if you can read that or know it, but really all you
really need the writings of the New Testament.
Yeah, yeah, but this can...
This can lead us down really bad paths.
Right, so I once years ago,
I'm gonna give no hints as to this was,
but I had an Orthodox clergyman say to me,
well, all that stuff in the law,
which is how he was referring to the Torah,
all that stuff in the law is an important anymore.
Mm.
Right.
All that's important is that we love God
with all our heart, soul, my strength
and love our neighbor is herself.
to which I replied, that's Deuteronomy and Leviticus.
Yeah.
Right. Yeah, a lot of the stuff that people think is introduced in the Gospels is simply
a quote from somewhere in the Torah.
Right. Right. So when Christ is asked, what is the first and greatest commandments? He
gives two commandments from the Torah. It says, these are the most important ones. Right?
Alright so that's it, this is a discussion about the Torah.
And so when we get to the famous passage in Matthew 5 that we've now alluded to many times
but have yet to read, where this, where Christ distinguishes between abolishing the Torah
and fulfilling it, we have to come to it with all of that in mind, with the reality of
what's in the Scriptures, right, with the reality of how the Gospels are
structures and what they...
structured in what they contain and how they relate to the Torah, if we want to understand
it correctly. Because if you go to any passage of the scriptures, you read it, you read
too small a part of it, and then try to take it at face value in some literal sense, and
then try to read everything else you encounter in the scriptures, according to what you think
that one verse said, you're gonna end up a Calvinist or something.
Yes.
Yeah, there are no skeleton keys to the Bible or many other things.
Many other.
Yes.
I just like to pick on Calvinists because some of my best friends are Calvinists.
Literally.
But yeah, so we need to bring or understanding of the reality of the scriptures to bear,
right, on how we interpret Christ's discussion in Matthew 5.
Yeah.
Yep.
Okay.
So before I read it, I actually just want to say hello to we have someone listening from
Shanghai, which is I think this is maybe the first time we've had someone actually in China
listening. So that's awesome. Someone from Canada, we have someone from Germany, someone
from Norway, and of course we love all you Americans as well.
So, you know, Kanaka stands seems so much less impressive when he got those others. We
still love you, Connecticut Stanies, but I mean, yes, barely a foreign country.
Wow.
We're not even 20 minutes in,
Roy getting already getting a little bit spicy.
Of course, Canaan does not really know
for its spicy foods, so.
That's true.
All right.
Matthew, you'll never see Poutine with jalapenos.
Let me put it to you now.
I bet that's a thing.
That's gotta be a thing.
Someone's doing that.
Someone's gonna write us right now
and send us pictures of their Poutine
with jalapenos in it.
Okay, Matthew chapter five, verses 17 through 20.
This is the Lord speaking.
Do not think that I have come to abolish the law or the prophets.
I have not come to abolish them but to fulfill them.
For truly I say to you until heaven and earth pass away, not a yod or timal will pass from
the law until all is accomplished.
Therefore, whoever relaxes one of the least of these commandments and teaches others to
do the same will be called least in the kingdom of heaven.
But whoever does them and teaches them will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.
I tell you.
unless your righteousness exceeds that of the scribes and Pharisees,
you will never enter the kingdom of heaven.
So this is kind of the core text of what we're going to be talking about in this
first half. Yeah.
And the first verse of that, and the last verse of that,
are the ones that tend to get broken off and used in weird ways.
Right, not related to the context.
So the first verse of that of course
is the do not think I've come to abolish the law or the prophets, the Torah or the prophets.
I've come not to abolish them, but to fulfill them.
And that's, you know, when you're having a discussion, right, and you try to point to
something in the Old Testament broadly, or the Torah in particular.
And whoever you're talking to says, oh, well, that's the Old Testament.
Right.
And...
You said we both well Christ Christ didn't abolish the Old Testament. They say no. He didn't abolish it. He fulfilled it right that quote that one verse. Yeah.
But they're quoting that verse as if to say, they're fulfilled abolished right. I mean, fulfill sounds nicer, but yeah. Yeah. Either way, you know, you're throwing it out the window. Right. Oh, we have we have a South African listening. That's there we go. Yeah.
And then the other one that sometimes gets brought, well, we'll start there.
So, the next few verses just like put to lie that interpretation.
Right?
Coscrice goes on to say, until heaven and earth pass away, and this has not happened yet,
sorry, preteris.
Not a yoder at Timmel will pass from the law until all is accomplished.
Right?
and a yod for the
of you who don't know anything about Hebrew kind of looks like an apostrophe. It's the smallest
letter of the Hebrew alphabet. And a timel is part of a letter that separates a het from a tet.
So it's not the smallest letter, not the smallest part of a letter. We'll pass from the Torah until
all is accomplished. Right? So all is accomplished here is connected to heaven and earth passing away.
So that
Now. Right. So none of those things are passing away. So fulfillment does not mean pass away. Right. For sure. Right.
And then the next verse takes even farther whoever relaxes one of the least of these commandments and teaches others to do the same will be called least in the kingdom of heaven.
But whoever does them and teaches them will be called great in the
kingdom of heaven. So not only do they not pass away, but whatever Christ means by fulfilled,
by the Torah being fulfilled by him means that we, who are seeking to enter the kingdom
of heaven, Christians, are going to be doing them and teaching them.
I don't see how you get much more clear than that.
Those verses also kind of mess with the Waiverse 20 is sometimes broken off and used weirdly,
and this is our Calvinist friends.
They'll kind of split it off from the context and say, I tell you, unless your righteousness
exceeds that of the scribes of Pharisees, you will never enter the kingdom of heaven, and
they use that to say, Ah, see, the scribes of the Pharisees, their righteousness is from the
law.
It's from the Torah.
Right.
you need Christ's righteousness which is greater than that.
Yeah, instead.
Right. And so here's the problem with that.
The people who are being talked about here are people who will not enter the kingdom of heaven.
And we're just told that the people who do and teach the commandments of the Torah
will be called great in the kingdom of heaven.
So if doing and teaching the commandments of the Torah
excludes you from the kingdom of heaven.
How can you also be great in the kingdom of heaven?
of heaven. Trying to do the math in my head here. Yes, yes. That math cannot be done. That circle
cannot be squared. Right. Right. So again, like, how many spreads you may have a bunch
of good points about this, but this verse should not be one of them because that's not
What is that?
Right.
Yeah.
So.
So
very clearly here, Christ is saying, it's not abolished.
None of it passes away.
It's fulfilled.
Not one stroke of a brush passes away.
Not one commandment should be taught against or relaxed.
Mm.
Or relaxed.
So again, fulfilled does not mean relaxed.
Because we tend to,
And we talked about this a little...
in a very old episode. There's this idea that Christ sort of fulfills different commandments
in different ways. Right? So when folks who want to use fulfilled to mean something like
abolished, they'll say, well, Christ fulfills like the moral law because he keeps all the
moral commandments.
in the Torah, but we still have to keep the moral commandments. Right? So he fulfills it because he
keeps them, but we should keep them too. Right? So I'm not even sure what fulfill means there,
if he's a V.S. But then they'll say, well, but he Christ fulfills the sacrificial system by his
sacrifice it therefore we don't do those anymore. So in that case,
We're feeling it means we don't do it.
Yeah. Right.
And so there's, I'll just say, it seems like the whole idea is,
how do we work this out so we don't have to do the stuff that's in the Torah?
That seems to be what it's about. Right. Right.
And, and as we're going to get into in the rest of this first half,
this is not a wheel you need to reinvent.
Right. People are trying to sort of reverse engineer Christian practice.
Right. They're trying to say, okay, well, we do keep these commandments about sexual
immorality, but we eat shrimp. Right. And probably somebody out there eats owls. Right.
So like how do you explain that and so there are all these attempts.
to reverse engineer and that's a very bad way to interpret scripture.
Right.
It's like like the the the presumption there is okay.
Okay, guys, I'm going to figure this out and now we can apply all this the correct way.
You know like like who cares how this has been being done for all these now thousands
of years.
We got to figure it out for ourselves.
We need to, you know.
We need to figure out what exactly does fulfillment mean and how does this apply and all these specific
I didn't come up with a new as you said to reinvent the wheel come up with a new system
Right, right and so in the pages of the scriptures themselves
Right, including the pages of the Torah itself
we have
The tools to understand
Why things came to be the way they are in the Christian church?
mm-hmm.
vis-a-vis the commandments of
the Torah. And that's a lot of what we're going to be getting into now for the rest of
this half. So let's say we're successful, right? In talking through the Gospels and going
through Matthew 5, like we just did to show, and this is in the sermon on the Mount. This
This is near the beginning of the sermon on the mount, just to locate that part.
That we read right so Christ is teaching this like right after the Beatitudes
Right, so this is this is part of the beginning. He's framing what he's about to teach everything
He's about to teach about the Torah and the commandments. He's framing with
I'm not getting rid of nothing
Right, I'm not even relaxing anything
right. This is going to continue to be done and taught, right within.
this. So even if, right, we do our jobs well or people who don't know who we are and
haven't heard this show, right, just read the text in an honest and straightforward way
and come to the same conclusion that this is what Christ is doing. There's still an issue
that crops up. Because there's this whole swath of people.
That's an interesting collection of people who have probably never been collected together
before.
Who, even if they're willing to accept Jesus as a teacher of Torah and an explainer
and interpreter of Torah, throw in a monkey ranch with St. Paul.
Yeah.
And I think the reason why the reason why the
gets done, or maybe I should say one of the big, yeah, I need to flip it on the other side.
One of the big consequences of why people think that there's this huge shift with St. Paul
is this idea that there was this religion called Judaism that was based on the Torah and that there's
this religion called Christianity. And St. Paul belongs to Judaism and he converts to Christianity
that there are these two different religions.
right. And so as we're going to see it here, there's all kinds of reasons why you might
want to say that. And one of the things that we're saying, and I think is a major, major
theme throughout this, the hundreds of hours we've spent on this podcast now, is that the
religion of the Old Testament and the religion of the New Testament, the religion of the
Christian church, same religion, the same religion.
It's not two different religions.
Right.
So, yes.
And that's especially connected in the case of Martin Luther.
But some of the people were going to talk about even precede Martin Luther.
So this isn't just something he starts, but this is something he returns to.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
And so there has been, since a very early period in the history of the church, a bad way
way to read things.
Paul. This may even be what St. Peter is referring to in second Peter, when he talks about the people who
talks about how there are some things in St. Paul's letters that are hard to understand and
people twist them to their own destruction, right? This may even be the particular reading he's
talking about. St. Paul even sometimes seems to elude to people understanding him that way
because when he does his rhetorical, is this what I'm saying? No, of course I'm not saying that.
So there's been this bad way of reading St. Paul very early probably from his, from some
of his critics during his lifetime, which is that he is speaking against Moses, against
the Torah saying, get rid of that stuff.
Now we got Jesus.
It's not important.
This effect is reading the...
all kinds of things in big and small ways.
An obvious early example would be the Marcy and I movements,
and the various Gnostic movements that adopted that position on the Old and New Testaments.
Yeah, and they were really explicit about it, too.
Like, God of the Old Testament is a different God, and He's evil,
and then forget about that stuff.
The Father of Jesus Christ is a different God.
Yeah, and and
and sorry, D.B.H., but saying that you think the evil Old Testament God doesn't exist doesn't make you not a Marcy Knight.
If the Nostek Shufitz, you must wear it.
So, yeah, and there's a whole swath of Nostek groups then that had a reading of St. Paul.
They tried to twist and use certain elements of St. Paul talking about the Torah to
try to say, yeah, see, this is bad, right? And to try to make this contrast with Christ, however
they saw Christ, because we're talking about Gnostic groups. So Jesus Christ logos, sometimes
these are separate emanations of something, right? You know, Gnostic's. But who tried
it's everywhere, drive this wedge, right?
But, you know, and let me...
say before I name any other groups, these are disparate groups.
These are an odd collection of disparate groups.
I'm not saying these groups are all the same, but they do have this one weird thing
in common. They have this one weird thing in common, but they are not the same.
Yeah.
So another group that does does this is dispensationalists, at least classical
dispensationalists.
Right.
There's a lot of different versions.
Because there's no pope of dispensationalism anymore.
Scofield died.
So how everyone could do what's right in their own eyes.
A great appointment to them all.
Yeah.
But so this sensationalism right will,
classically, affirmed, yes,
Jesus is talking about the Torah all the time.
And so those things that Jesus teaches
in the gospels,
don't apply to the church.
Those are going to apply to the Jewish people in the Millennial Kingdom when they return to Christ.
When they return to Jesus, it says to Messiah.
And so, what St. Paul writes, that's directed toward the church.
And the church is for them in Nately, non-Jewish, in Nately Gentile.
Not made up of a mix, just the church's Gentiles.
Yeah, and so again, right, though, for very
different reasons. They end up reading St. Paul in much the same way. Right? That St. Paul is,
there's this break a distinction between Christ and St. Paul. Right? And that St. Paul is
arguing for, forget about that Torah stuff. Right? We're doing a whole new thing now. Right?
And frankly, there's at least a light strain of that, even outside dispensationalism and
evangelicalism in that when you look at issues like worship.
There's an assumption that, as St. Paul is planting churches, he's essentially starting
worship from scratch.
Right.
None of the things with incense or sacrifice or any of that, even very much of the synagogue
stuff is carried over into Christian worship.
Christian worship is just this simple thing that happens in people's houses.
Yeah.
where a few songs are sung in somebody reads scripture and preaches.
which looks awful lot like what folks are doing, you know,
a couple thousand years later suspiciously,
being projected into the past.
But, um,
there's sort of that assumption of starting from scratch,
which is sort of a light version of this, right?
But still points to some kind of distinction where St. Paul is taking
at least parts of the Torah and setting it aside.
Um,
I'm going to go ahead and say it.
This is going to sound like a cheap shot.
shot. To some people.
But I do not mean it as a jeep shot.
Now that that disclaimer will help.
And I will clarify after I say this to what I mean by it.
So there is this division classically that comes out
of John Calvin, but is in a lot of Protestantism
and evangelicalism, where you divide the law
into these three parts, the civil law,
the ceremonial law, and the moral law.
Yeah.
And that's the b-
for your average evangelical or even confessional Protestant person,
some version of that is part of this explanation or reconstruction.
So it's not like a Marcy Knight position where there's this total break.
It's sort of a partial break.
So this is just a historical point.
Historically, the first place where we see the commandments of the Torah broken up,
like that is in a Nostick text from the late second and early third century called the letter
to Ptolemy. How about that? And that that Nostick text is deliberately trying to find like
a compromise between Marcianism and what the Orthodox Church was teaching. So he's deliberately
trying, now I'm not saying this, we're Calvin God it. In fact, I'm pretty sure Calvin never
do that existed.
I'm not saying evangelicals or nostics, right?
Some of them probably are, but I'm not saying all of them are.
I'm not saying that.
I'm just saying, historically, this is the first place where we see that kind of argument.
And you can understand historically why in that historical setting that kind of argument
would emerge.
And it's a species of this same kind of argument for a disjunction, either partial or
total.
Going back.
to people who thought there was a total disjunction.
So far we've had no stakes at dispensationalists,
and now we have Friedrich Nietzsche.
Wait, what?
All hanging out together at a party.
What kind of playlist would we put together?
Anyway, it looks exhausting.
So, and Nietzsche took this in a way
that's very counterintuitive,
based on what we've heard.
already said about scripture and based on subsequent
theological and philosophical history.
But Nietzsche thought there was this complete break
between Christ and St. Paul, but he thought it went the other way.
Meaning, from Nietzsche's point of view,
Christ was an example of the upper bench.
He comes along, he re-values all values,
you'll see transforms everything.
Things.
completely outside the box.
Through us preaching calls into view a whole new world,
a whole new way of ordering the world
and possibilities and everything.
And then for Nietzsche, St. Paul comes along
and judyizes it.
Wait, what?
Yes.
St. Paul comes along and just turns it like wrenches it back
into this Jewish mold.
Wow.
For the Pharisee.
So.
Right.
I'm sorry.
So he's included here, even though he's kind of the inverse, right?
He still has this break, this idea that there's this big break between what St. Paul is doing
and saying and writing and what, what Jesus did.
Next up is Islam.
Yeah, well, which means if we're well already with the dispensationalists, we couldn't have
alcohol at our party, but now we definitely can.
which means the Nietzsche is gonna be...
board. But this is a major move, of course, within Islam. Right? Because Islam teaches
dogmatically that Jesus is the Jewish Messiah. They believe in his virgin birth. And they
believe he was a prophet. Now, however, they believe he was a prophet who taught Islam.
So I'll feel good to see.
that, then they need somebody who came up with Christianity. So they pick St. Paul.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. St. Paul made this up. And some of the more advanced modern versions
of this, and I say modern because honestly, like these aren't arguments you would have heard
being made at the Caliphate against St. John of Damascus. Right. These are modern arguments
based on modern biblical scholarship in a lot of cases.
But they've tried.
to revise St. Peter and St. James into being totally different people than they're presented
as by history or the scriptures in order to make them also kind of Islamic like they're
the real heirs of Jesus and St. Paul comes and like stages this coup or something when
he creates Christianity.
But again, there's this huge divide.
And then of course as I just...
kind of alluded to modern scholarship does this all the time.
Yeah.
Cause they're just trying to take the whole thing apart, frankly.
Yeah. Yeah.
And having done a lot of work in St. Paul recently, um,
I have less and less appreciation for this.
And I think it's dumber and dumber.
Hmm.
Um,
because, you know, the kind of things they point to
are like linguistic things.
things. Like Christ talks about the kingdom of God a lot.
It's say Paul only uses that term a couple of times.
Um, okay. Yeah. Like it's that level of stuff.
That good. Yeah. Yeah. Like, say Paul doesn't use the same words.
Jesus did.
Right?
So, you know, Jesus says,
uh, love
Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind and strength and love your neighbor as yourself.
The whole Torah is summed up in these two commandments.
And St. Paul says the one who loves keeps the whole Torah. See, he uses totally different
words. They're totally at odds with each other. Yeah. Yeah. So, I mean, you know, normally we
reserve calls to the second half. But we actually have someone calling who has a question that is
directly connect
to what we're talking about right this moment.
So I thought I was going to hit it.
Is it Bart Irman?
It's, I, I don't think so.
OK, it's not friend of the show, Bart Irman.
No.
Because if he calls in, if he ever calls in,
yeah, it doesn't matter what half.
He gets pretty through.
Yeah, let him in Elijah if Bart Irman calls in.
No, no, this is, this is actually Michelle from, uh, from Florida.
So Michelle, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Are you there?
Oh, yeah.
Hi.
Thank you.
Bye.
Welcome. You are probably the first person ever to get in during the first half.
Yes. I'm flattered. I'm truly flattered. Thank you.
You yourself have staged a coup.
Thank you. Oh, you want my question, obviously.
Yes. So what's on your mind? What's on your mind, myself?
Let's want to talk about WrestleMania. I'll talk about that.
I have no expertise in that. I'm sorry.
to understand why there was such limited Christian resistance to Hitler, given that we share
the same commandment, right? And it just seemed to me that we're kind of all Jews in
spirit if you want to use that term. And so I can't understand. It wasn't just one branch
Christianity. It was right across the board. I think the
objections I've ever read about were from the Greek orthodox archbishop's in
In Greece obviously and you know Roddy Edmunds who who's famous phrase was
were all Jews here and so I'm just trying to understand why was that is that
because of what you were talking about earlier that you know the strict
Protestants really didn't didn't see it that way I'm sorry I'm not phrasing that
very well but I just wondered if you had an opinion on that.
Yeah. Yeah.
I think the first thing I'll say is there certainly were plenty of Christians in Europe,
including in Germany, who resisted what Hitler was doing to the Jews.
I think it wasn't it, Father, was it a Dietrich Bonheffer? Was the one that I'm blanking?
Right to assassinate him? Yeah. Yeah, Dietrich Bonheffer.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, so I mean that definitely existed and certainly outside of
Germany, right? There were there were people who resisted that largely on the basis, say,
like, look, these are human beings and human beings shouldn't be treated this way. But at
the same time, I mean, there was a lot of people who agreed with Hitler, right? And I, my
sense, and now mind you, World War II is not my area of history, so I'm not really an expert
on this. But my sense is that when people
maybe engaged in a little bit of Marcianism, that is to say this kind of rejection or at least
marginalization of the Old Testament.
You know, as part of this, it was largely to justify the way that they already wanted to behave.
Much like, for instance, in 19th century America, people used passages from Scripture to justify race-based slavery.
Right, it wasn't because like the
read the Bible and concluded, oh, we should be keeping slaves, you guys. No, it was, oh, we have
slaves. And yeah, I'm still a good Christian. In fact, here's a Bible verse, you know, I think that
that's more the way that it went. I don't think that World War II, era, and previous anti-Semitism
and the Holocaust and so forth was based on a reading of the scripture. I don't know. Correct me if
I'm wrong about that father.
Yeah, so...
You're writing that right ideas don't cause things.
People do things and they generate the ideologies they need to justify them, right, to do work
for them.
You have to, I mean, I don't want to pull a put in here, but you have to go back a few
centuries in Germany. And you have to look at Martin Luther. Sorry.
Luther in Prince. I am not I'm not arguing here that you are fruit of the poison tree or something,
but we have to be honest about the historical person Martin Luther. Yeah. Oh yeah, the fifth book
of Luther, is that right? Yeah. Other Steven, do we lose you? Oh wow, this is like the old days.
Oh yeah. Oh there he is. Martin Luther, his continue.
existence after breaking within being excommunicated from the Roman Catholic Church,
depended on the goodwill of certain German princes.
And so, not so much theologically, but in matters related to it.
Kind of breaking up there a little bit.
But this is like the old days of Lord of Spirits.
It's exciting.
As it revolt, he justified and encouraged the princes to murder thousands of peasants.
You can see this with the crushing of the Anabaptist movement, Germany.
And he did this with on the Jews in their lives where he called for synagogues to be burned,
Torah books to be burned, which was to justify what those German princes were doing in
wanting to seize the wealth and land and holdings of Jewish people who had accumulated some wealth
within Germany. So they were otherwise, their things were taken, they were killed,
Luther justified it in service to those princes. And so that ideology became baked into the German
state as it formed.
Hitler did not just come along and start anti-Semitism.
There were pogroms, there were outbreaks of violence against Jews for centuries all through there.
What Hitler was doing, and so the state Protestant churches in Europe had bought into that ideological superstructure by the time Hitler came along.
When we're talking
about the Roman Catholic Church, it's a little different. The Roman Catholic Church had gotten into bed with colonialism.
One of the things people, there's some good books on this that have been published in the last decade or so.
But one of the things people don't realize as Hitler formulated as plans was Germany didn't have any colonies,
like Britain or France or Belgium or Portugal or Spain.
So his idea was to colonize the Slavic lands.
His plan, his overarching plan, was not even primarily focused on the Jews.
His primarily focused on, he wanted to kill 90% of the Slavs and enslave the rest and
put them to work and make everything east of him greater, a greater Germany, essentially
have it as colonies. And all this
This stuff he wanted to do was the stuff that like Belgium had done in the Congo, that
Britain had done in India, that Spain had done in various places, that the United States
had done in Cuba at one point.
And so the Roman Catholic Church along the way with the settlement of the New World and
these things, had put similar elements of ideological superstructure in place that can
that kind of behavior overseas,
could don't that kind of behavior in the colonies,
because of what now seem horrifically racist comments
about the Native populations.
One of the heroes of the settlement of Central and South
Americas, Bartella, Mayo, De las Casas,
who managed to argue the Pope into seeing the indigenous people
people of North and South America.
America is human, but in the process he sold out Africans.
And gave his blessing to the Pope blessing the slave trade from Africa.
I was just saying, I just want to add one other piece of context, which is that, I mean,
you know, this episode is not about anti-Semitism.
Although there's like, you know, right, when you start to reject the Old Testament in this
and kind of gets raised to some extent.
It is tied up in this.
Yeah.
When you read 19th century biblical scholarship
from Germany, like it's there.
Right, right.
But I mean, I should say like.
And how they feel, testament.
Like, like I know that, you know, sometimes,
you know, Orthodox people sometimes like
to point the finger at our Protestant and Catholic friends
and say, look at these problems you guys have had.
We never, we've never had that issue, whatever.
Oh, no.
The reality is.
So under the czar, there were similar things.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
about Jews in Russia in the world.
Yeah, I mean, there were literally like most of Russia Jews were not even allowed to live during what was called the pale of settlement, right?
You know, like they only could live west of a certain line and there were treated super badly, you know, but this was this question was specifically about Hitler and about Hitler because he was after the sloths
That made the Russians and the Russia lights his natural enemies, right? Yeah
Yeah.
So but, but.
So where I'm going with this is so the Roman Catholic Church also had that ideological superstructure in place that could be used to justify those things.
And I think one of the things that happens after World War II is that just the level of those atrocities and the fact that those atrocities were committed in Europe so they were in front of everyone.
Right. People in Europe and the United States didn't see what was happening in the Congo.
Yeah, right they didn't know
really know. But when it was sort of revealed in their faces and everyone knew and couldn't
avoid it, that started to break down that ideological superstructure. And those things have
become much less justifiable now. Right? Much less justifiable now. And so I don't
I think it's directly...
related that now people are sort of reassessing the relationship between old and New Testaments and that kind of thing.
I think that's more related to discovering the Dead Sea Scrolls, some other textual discoveries and that kind of thing.
But it has certainly cleared some space.
It has made those kind of ideas that were used to justify that kind of thing much more unacceptable.
and B
being more unacceptable now, kind of a space is open up.
As a long response, Michelle, does that hit to your question?
Yeah, no, no, I'm just super grateful.
That was really helpful.
I think it's interesting to note that the first thing
that the Germans did when they invaded Poland
is to round up all the Catholic priests
so in these small villages and send them to Dockhouse.
I mean, I have relatives who,
part of the slot at Call of Call.
So, I understand, I mean, you know, people don't probably know.
Thank you, Father, for mentioning that 11 million slots
died as well as the six million Jews.
So yes, that was really, really helpful for the context.
And it does, yeah, it answers my question.
I'm sorry to have taken up so much time.
No, no.
I mean, you know, we can always cut you off.
So you think on this show, we worry about going along.
Is this your first episode? Oh no, no, I'm done over 300 hours of your other podcast.
All right. A true fan. Yes. Yeah. All right. Thank you very much for calling into that.
Thank you. All right. Okay. Yes.
Yes, right.
Yes, so interesting.
Let's ask six dispensationalists, Nietzsche, Islam, modern.
and you know, Biblical scholars and no by the way, you know, state worshiping anti-Semites.
Yeah. Yeah.
I'll have this one weird thing in common.
Yeah.
They, they, on some level reject the Old Testament and, and wanted, you know, separated from the
New Testament in one way or another.
But isn't that justified? Isn't that what St. Paul said?
We actually had someone ask in one of the comments like, wait, you said the, the religion of the Old Testament,
the religion, the Old Testament, the
New Testament or the same religion, well, St. Paul, he doesn't say that in his letters.
He says the opposite.
As I responded, well, keep listening.
Because literally those categories he was in.
The next thing we're going to talk.
Yeah, exactly.
Are you a modern scholar, a dispensationalist, a Muslim, a non-Ansic?
Are you a preacher in each?
So if you are, please call in to the show.
Yes.
Are you that hologram that Jordan Peterson was talking to be about?
Let's dig to the shop.
in the YouTube chat.
Oh wow.
That's a story for another time.
Yeah.
Yeah, so what does St. Paul say about this?
Does he regard himself as making some kind of
disjunction from the old test running from the Torah?
So, well, other than continually saying the opposite,
right?
Over and over and over again throughout the book of Acts.
There's lots.
I mean, this isn't enough itself.
We could do a whole episode on just St. Paul's view
of the Torah.
right? And who knows what lies of the future, but that's not tonight. But we have just a couple of
examples, right? A couple of examples of the way St. Paul talks about the Torah that kind of put the lie
to this idea that he was somehow opposed to it. Yeah, yeah. So Exhibit A, Romans chapter 2,
versus 12
through 16. He says, for all who have sinned without the law, and we should understand, by the way,
that law in the New Testament is referring to the Torah. So I'm going to actually just go ahead and
say the Torah, because I think that makes it a little bit clearer for us. For all who have sinned
without the Torah will also perish without the Torah, and all who have sinned under the Torah will be
judged by the Torah. For it is not the hearers of the Torah who are righteous before God, but the
doers of the Torah who will be justified.
For when Gentiles who do
do not have the Torah by nature do with the Torah requires, they are a Torah to themselves,
even though they do not have the Torah. They show that the work of the Torah is written
on their hearts, but their conscience also bears witness, and their conflicting thoughts
accuse or even excuse them. On that day when, according to my gospel, God judges the secrets
of men by Christ Jesus.
Yes, so this is in the past I've done my list.
of people who the Bible says kept the Torah perfectly, which gets many people upset
among our Protestant friends. But one of those groups on the list is from what we just
read, some Gentiles. Yeah. Right. Some Gentiles. Because St. Paul is a presenting this as a
hypothetical. Right. Hypothetically, some Gentile could just...
you know, be a really good guy and keep all the commandments even though he hasn't heard the Torah.
He's saying this happens. Yeah, he doesn't say if Gentiles do this, he says when Gentiles do this.
Do this. They show that. Yeah, right. This is an actual thing. Right. And
and St Paul is using this as an argument against the Jewish Christians who he's writing to in Rome.
Right?
So Paul writes the epistle to the Romans after the Claudian expulsion of the Jews from Rome to try to help reconcile which was for two years to try to help reconcile the Jewish and
non-Jewish Christians in Rome, right, and so in chapter one of Romans
He's spent some time talking about how horrible the Gentile world was before the gospel came into it how sinful how wicked
how idolatrous
Right, but then...
He also in chapter two turns turns to the Jewish Christians and says now before you get all excited
You had the Torah
Right did you keep it?
Did you actually keep the commandments?
Because the Saint Paul says it's not the person who hears it
It's not the person who goes to the synagogue and hears somebody read the Torah
Who's justified who's in the right right who's a righteous person?
It's the person who actually does what it is.
it says. And he's holding up, you know, there are Gentiles out there who have never heard
the Torah in their lives, never seen a synagogue. Don't know what a Torah is, right? But who
have kept it better than you because it's written on their hearts. And those Gentiles
who never heard a word of it are going to be at a better place as he says at the end,
Right? When? When? God through Christ.
judges the world they're going to be at a better place than you are if you
heard the Torah and didn't keep it. Yeah, right. But so where in here is he
saying the Torah is bad? I mean, the opposite he essentially was like even the
people who don't have it, they have it if they do it. Right, you know, and the
mark of them being righteous people, and being proud to be righteous people
the day of judgment will be that they have kept it.
Yeah. Even without having heard it.
Yeah.
Right?
And the condemnation of Jewish people who haven't kept it is going to be by the Torah.
And notice, he says, this condemnation, so if he's talking about, is when Christ returns to judge the earth.
When Christ returns to judge the earth, they're going to be judged according to the Torah.
He says because Christ is in a very real sense.
the last word of the Torah.
Right.
And so it's not that you were in the past,
you were judged according to the Torah,
and now you're going to be judged
according to something else.
Yeah, no, which is superseded it.
Right.
That's not what he says.
And he's writing entirely to Christians here.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right.
Jewish Christians and Gentile Christians.
Galatians 5 verse 14 is what I quoted earlier
or what I was joking about the different phrase.
right? Yeah. Where? This is where he says, you know, for the whole laws fulfilled in one word,
you should love your neighbor as yourself. Right. Totally different than what Jesus said, because
it's phrased somewhat differently in the Greek. Yeah. It's so, and we could go on and on and on.
And again, these are from Galatians and Romans. Galatians and Romans are the two epistles where he
supposedly is saying bad things about the Torah.
He sells elsewhere, the one who loves keeps the whole Torah.
He's taking the same approach to the Torah that Jesus did.
But we have this fundamental fact that we've already mentioned.
In the church, throughout her history, the Torah has been seen to apply to Jewish Christians
and Gentile Christians differ.
differently, right, at bare minimum. And the answer to why this is, right, the answer
to why I can enjoy a good crawfish boil here, even during Lent is found in Acts chapter 15,
there you go, which interestingly enough is another place people go when they're trying
to say the law has been done away with.
Right.
That's like read the
read the chapter everybody.
So what happens in Acts 15 is called the Council of Jerusalem.
Yeah, this is the apostles getting together to talk about basically the big controversy
about Gentiles becoming Christians.
Do they need to be circumcised?
Do they need to be circumcised to receive the Eucharist?
Right.
Too often that Eucharist part gets left out.
That's right.
Yeah, and calling it a council is kind of anachronistic and kind of not.
It's anachronistic in the sense that we're using council the way we talk about later church
councils, right?
And this is obviously before councils were a formal thing, but at the same time, the
council of Jerusalem really sets the paradigm and the structure, including the phrasing of
the proclamation at the end that's going to be used in later church councils.
Yeah, because they'll they'll all say it's seen
good to the Holy Spirit and to us, which is literally a quotation from the Apostolic
Council on Jerusalem.
Yeah, so this is sort of the Ur-Council, right?
This is like ecumenical Council zero, right?
This is, or negative one, I guess, minus one for doing the Godzilla thing.
So right, there is this issue, right?
this issue about circumcision and it relates to the Eucharist.
Right because
Within Judaism there was not let me say this first, right
Just as today
There were not Jewish people going around trying to circumcise Gentiles and get them to become Jews in general
Yeah, it was not a
Evangelistic right this was not a thing
right
Not a thing that happened so when we see
These people from the party of the Pharisees in Acts 15,
so we see Pharisees wanting to circumcise Gentiles
that should trigger so we should go away to second.
What's Y?
Why would they want to do that?
Why would they think that was necessary?
Well, if you go back in Exodus to when the Passover was given.
I believe this is in Exodus chapter 14,
during one of the reiterations.
Right, it is stated that.
Everyone who eats the Passover must be circumcised.
That Gentiles, right, Sojourners, could come and live in the land of Israel and not become
Israelites.
Right, they didn't have to to live there.
But if they wanted to eat the Passover, then they and their household had to be...
circumcised and become Israelites.
So Christ, of course, institutes the Eucharist at the Passover.
And the practice of the Eucharist and the way it was seen, as we've talked about in
the show, our episode on the Eucharist and other places, is deeply embedded in what's
going on in the Passover.
And so this was viewed.
Right, by the early Christians as a ritual sacrifice, it's very closely connected to the
Passover.
And so the question really was, yeah, it's cool that these Gentiles are coming because
of the Messiah to come and worship the God of Israel with us.
This is wonderful.
This is beautiful.
This is something that was prophesied in the Hebrew Scriptures.
the Messiah came this would happen.
Are they allowed to eat the Passover?
Are they allowed to eat the Eucharist?
If they haven't been circumcised.
So this is a question about how does the Eucharist,
the Christ Institute, how does that relate to the very particular set
of commandments and regulations in the Torah?
This is a TORIC
question. Okay, this is a Torah question. And so these people from the party of the Pharisees with the one view
come to the apostles led by St. James who ultimately issues the decision, not St. Peter.
I don't know why I had to point that out. But yeah,
And to get a ruling, right, what is the ruling for our communities, right?
leaders, what is the ruling for our communities in terms of how we apply that part of the Torah
in terms of our practice? Right? And so this is how the issue is ultimately decided. Right? Is
St. James, in particular, who we know even from outside of the scriptures, even from like Josephus,
was this and
incredibly pious Jewish man who knew the Torah who spent so much time praying in the temple
He had calluses on his knees so his knees his legs look like camel legs
Right that's what I told you see this
Renowned among all the the Jewish people even those who weren't Christians for his piety right
He makes a ruling and he makes that ruling based based on the Torah not based on setting aside the Torah
because if you go
to chapters 17 through roughly 23 people disagree whether it ends in 23, 24, 26.
Because you know you got to publish papers about something. There's what is called
in Leviticus the holiness code. And most of the commandments within the
holiness code are prefaced with God, speaks to Moses and says, say to the sons
of Israel.
Da da da da da. Right? So, chapter 19 has a bunch of food laws. Right? Say to the the
sons of Israel of the owl of the night hawk in the sparrow that shall not eat. Right?
That's of course both the Spook King James English as we know. What else? Speak in my house.
right so but there are other places there are other places
like Leviticus 18, which gives the commandments about sexual morality, where God says to Moses,
say to the sons of Israel, and all of the strangers and foreigners who live in the land.
And then gives the commandments.
So there are some commandments in the Torah on a very literal reading.
In fact, most of the Commandants of the Torah apply to Israelites.
And then there is a subset of those commandments that apply both to the Israelites and to
anyone who is living in the land.
Yeah.
Right.
Anyone who is living in the land.
And so what St. James does is he looks at this and says, okay, well, these are Gentiles.
I don't see anything in the Hebrew script.
St. Paul will agree with this. You'll say the same thing.
Markable, how St. James and St. Paul actually agreed. Sorry Muslims.
That says that these people are going to stop being. When they come to worship, the God of Israel, they're going to stop being whatever they were.
They're going to stop being Greeks. They're going to stop being Egyptians. They're going to stop, right. In fact, quite the opposite.
opposite. Right what those prophecies.
about the nations say over and over again is that those nations and their kings are going
to come and make these offerings.
Right?
Are going to come and worship the God of Israel.
It doesn't say they're all going to become Israelites ever.
Yeah.
All the nations will come and worship Israel's God.
Right.
And so, like James says, they don't need to become Jewish.
And therefore, since they're not becoming Jewish, right?
They are only responsible for the commandments that are directed toward those who live in the land.
They're not responsible for, therefore they can eat an owl.
They can't be sexually immoral.
Yeah, and no idolatry.
Right.
Right no idolatry and if you look in the holiness code the reason I brought the holiness code in particular is that there are
places where the commandments are applied to everyone and they are sexual
immorality, idolatry and in two places that you can't consume blood. Which this is
literally the list that's an accident. Right,
those are the four commands. That's why I focused on the Holiness code. Right?
So, ladies and gentlemen, here's the four commandments that everyone has to
these are the ones, these are the ones that you need to
keep by the way, those are still part of orthodox canon law, those still apply to you,
including the whole blood eating thing. But right, but the other ones, if you're not
Jewish, do not apply to you. God didn't command you to do those things. And this is what,
so for example, in Galatians, when St. Paul says to Gentile Christians, if you go and get
circumcised you have to keep the whole
This is what he means.
Right, you want to become Jewish, you're gonna have to become Jewish.
Now, he'll go further, he'll say other things, like he'll say, you know, right now you have these promises in Christ.
And so if you go and get circumcised, you're basically saying, ah, forget about Christ, I'm gonna go keep Torah.
Obviously, that's a problem, right?
That's what he means by cutting yourself off from Christ.
But he also makes the point, right?
Now you're bound to the whole law, right?
And this is how Romans two can work by the way.
Because if when we went through Romans two,
you might have been thinking, really,
there was something like random Roman out there
who somehow like never ate shrimp, never, right?
Did any of those that, right?
Right, right.
He wasn't responsible for any of those things.
He's not an Israelite.
Right. Right. Gentiles keeping kosher. Right. Like why would they?
Like what weird confluence of of of coincidence would they have to be that there are some Gentiles
somewhere keeping kosher. Yeah, accidentally. Um, right. But that's not required of him. Right.
That's not required of him by the Torah. Right. Um, and this is not by the way, just to be clear,
This is not something like St. James.
came up with. This is not like, oh man, this is a real problem. What are we going to do? Well,
here, hey, have you noticed this in Leviticus, right? There was all, this was already firmly established
in terms of Jewish interpretation of the Torah. And an example of this from the Second Temple periods,
so pre-Christian, the Second Temple period is in the Book of Jubiles. And the way it's presented in
of the Book of Jubilee's.
is not in terms of the holiness code, but in terms of Noah, right? Because after the flood, right,
Noah's the father of everybody, right? Shem is one of his sons, and then one of those sons
goes on from Shem's line comes Abraham from Abraham's line comes Israel, right? But Noah's everybody's
stat, whether you're European, African, Asian, right.
And so the book of Jubilee's goes there and comes up with basically the same list.
Right, basically. Now murder is added, but I think we were kind of clear on the murder being bad thing.
Right. I don't think St. James needed to reiterate that.
To to Gentile Christians, by the way, no murder.
Right.
good after theft, right?
You know, yeah.
But so this was already something, this was already a known principle that, and this is why,
this is why Israelites and later Jewish people didn't go out and try to convert Gentiles
in terms of, convert them in terms of, right, they're happy for them to give up idolatry
and worship the true God, but didn't go out and, you know, try and get them to get circumcised
or try and get them to...
keep kosher, right?
Trying to get their neighbors to stop eating pork, right?
Because that's not how they understood it.
They understood it as, no, we don't.
Right.
And that's not, that's not given to them.
And so what St. Paul is constantly doing, right?
St. Paul is not trying to make overarching rules
or lay down principles or construct
this new religion, Christian.
Christianity
Because he doesn't think there is one
St. Paul's a Pharisee his whole life. He was Jewish his whole life
So were the other apostles
Right not Pharisees but Jewish right their whole lives
They didn't think they had a new religion at all, right?
But what's St. Paul in particular is doing because he's going out and planting church communities in these
pagan Gentile cities that have a membership that is part Jewish Christian and
part Gentile Christians. He's constantly working to navigate between those two
and bring those two groups together as one. And everything he says about the Torah
is in that context. It's not in the context of what still applies and what
doesn't for all Christians or morale.
non-Christians. He's not talking about any of that, right? It's how do Jewish Christians and Gentile Christians
who live differently in some ways but share a
certain part of their life as Christians together.
How do we keep them together? How do they live together? How do they function together? That's what he's doing.
Yep.
I'll also...
I also want to recommend everyone by the way.
If you want a really long and detailed description of what's going on in the book of Romans,
you know, Father Stephen has that on the whole Council of God podcast.
So, all right.
Well, it's been a good beefy first half.
We're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back with the next
half of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymeck and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of-
give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Everybody.
It's one of my favorite commercials that we just heard.
It's a nice long one.
So, uh, yes. Yes.
This is a, uh, uh, go ahead.
Sorry, I was taking a power nap.
Oh!
Wake up, Father Steven. Get back to work.
Yeah. Yeah.
So you really, you really missed an opportunity there, you guys.
To do the, I'm Father Andrew Steven Demick, and I'm Richard Roland.
And we are...
I wonder what you would have said.
because we are the vacayers.
Right?
No, it's just, yeah.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Maybe we are the defenders of the earth.
I don't know.
Yeah, yeah.
And this one is on YouTube, everybody.
So look up the great tales on YouTube,
and you can subscribe and check out the trailer.
Last time we played this commercial,
I told everybody that one of my podcasts was going to die
because this new one is being born later this year.
And people got freaked out.
They're like, wait, is it Lord of Spirits is dying?
Is it Amman's soul?
is it the ear-yopic?
guess is it something else and it has not yet been revealed what it will be.
So I like the mental image that you just gave of like each of your podcasts beginning in this
parasitic phase. And then like consuming one of your previous podcasts and leaving its
withered hollowed out husk behind as it emerges to life. Exactly. I mean, there's there's only so much
time, one has a
the day. So also, I will point out that every episode of this podcast is the last episode
until the next one comes out. That's right. Well, especially when the next episode comes
out, then the previous one becomes the last episode is even more so the last episode.
Exactly. Exactly. So that, you know, that last episode we did, that was our last episode.
Yeah.
Now we're on this one.
So, yes.
So we're talking Torah, Torah, eh.
and Torah, or Torah, Torah, Torah.
And we, I think we actually do have some,
I'm not sure, it looks like there's some calls coming in,
but...
Let's do this.
Yeah, that's right.
So is anybody we can connect with now?
I'm going to Leroy Jenkins, this first call.
Oh man.
What's with that?
So, okay, well, we have, we have Bob calling.
His phone says it's from Massachusetts,
but who knows, where is Bob?
Where are you, Bob?
Can you hear me, Father?
Yes, we hear you. Welcome to Lord's Spirit's podcast.
All right, I'll stand in. Yeah, I do normally live in Massachusetts. I'm in Korea right now, so it's the morning show for me.
Oh, okay. You do sound like you're from Massachusetts. Yeah, I was going to say I still hear a little Massachusetts, so they can take you out of Massachusetts, but not it out of you.
You can't take I'm from the North Shore Abost and you can't escape it.
All right, what's on your mind?
So I just had a quick clarifying question.
Father's, so I'm wondering.
So my understanding is that we understand the church to be Israel, right?
Am I correct in this before I continue?
Yes.
All right.
So I guess I'm just wondering like.
if we understand the truth.
to be Israel. And we are all, you know, full, you know, participating members of the church,
which is Israel, you know. I'm not quite still understanding how even though we are Gentiles,
we are treated according to the law and stuff still like foreigners and
So, John, is there a question make sense?
Sure, sure.
Yeah, well, I mean, there's a couple ways to understand it,
right, like on the one hand,
there is this, and this will probably be a good future episode,
I think, Father, but there's the sense that the church
is the reconstitution of Israel
because of Israel having been scattered into the nations,
right, those 10 Northern tribes
and scattered into the nation.
So there is this regathering of Israel, right? But also that Israel is not the same thing as being Jewish
Right, I mean the word Jewish or Judean refers to Judeans
But but um
Someone can participate in Israel without being Jewish like that is an actual possibility
Right, so
Well, yeah, we'll talk more about that, but um, I don't know father. Do you want to
You want to address this? Yeah. So, um,
the
one of the key things and this really comes out of St. Paul is that,
um, he doesn't see, not only does he not see,
um, different.
So I don't like even though the Latin word,
until this means nations, I don't really like Gentiles because it has these ethnic connotations now.
Um.
But people from different nations, right? Because nobody's like just a Gentile, right? We're from
someone, right? We're something in particular. But not only does St. Paul not see people from all
these other nations coming and becoming Jewish in order to enter the church. He also doesn't see
Everyone, including Jewish people, Greek people, Roman people, Ethiopia.
Egyptians, the people who, St. Paul, would have encountered Samaritans, Syrians. He doesn't see them
coming into the church and no longer being Egyptians or Greeks or Jewish or any of these things.
So it's neither extreme. It's not sort of we come into the church and now we're just Christians and we're not any of those things anymore.
And it's also not on the other side, well, we all become Jewish.
Right, and this comes out of the prophecies about the nations coming to worship the God of Israel
that talk about the nations bringing their treasures.
Right, bringing in their treasures to give to God.
And the understanding that those treasures are all of the uniqueness and all of the particularity of,
You know, now we have a more expensive list, right?
Of Greek culture, Italian culture, American culture.
right, Mexican culture, Korean culture, Russian culture, right, all of the best, all of the
treasures of those particularities, right, we bring with us when we become Russian Christians,
Korean Christians, American Christians, Greek Christians, French Christians, etc., etc.
And in terms of the sojourners issue, I think the way...
that's dealt with in the New Testament is not by, I mean on one hand, St. Paul will say things like
you who were far off have now been brought near. Right. And it's very much wanting to argue in Romans
like no neither the Jewish Christians nor the Christians from the nations are second class citizens.
Right. Neither of them are second class citizens. But the way that's resolved seems to me to be with
with what St. Peter says, which is we should
But all be living like aliens and sojourners in this world.
That none of us should be seeking power and authority in this world.
None of us should be seeking to control institutions in this world.
That all of us should be living that way, whether Jewish or not as Christians, because
our actual homeland, our ultimate homeland is one that we will all share together.
right in the in the new heavens the new earth and the life of the world to come.
Does that make sense?
Yes, it does Father. Thank you.
All right. Thank you very much for calling.
I wonder if you can get Duncan Donuts coffee in Korea.
I, if not, I feel for the man.
You might go into withdrawal.
I mean, it's I can't I can't even I think it's got to be some time in the morning there in Korea.
I'm not sure what the time zone is there, but
Yeah, we've got people except Antarctica.
We have people on every continent listening tonight.
That's cool.
If you were at the Russian research station, call us now.
Yes.
We will have a, I don't know, some kind of crazy record or whatever.
But yeah.
So all right.
Thank you very much for calling us Bob.
We're going to go ahead and take one more question
before we move on.
This one comes from Daniel.
So Daniel, welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hi, Father.
Can you hear me?
We can hear you.
But it's on your mind.
All right, so my question was about Noah.
And he took, you know, it said that he took two of every kind of animal and seven of every kind of, you know, clean animal on the earth.
And sorry, I was wondering, well, you know, he's not a Jewish, that not a thing yet.
And so what's up with there?
or being a different clean and unclean animals,
at least one that he knows about that he can appreciate.
Yeah, what's with that?
I mean, it seems kind of anachronistic.
The clean and unclean stuff hasn't been given yet.
So what's that about, Father Steven?
So there are a couple of pieces here,
but we have to remember Genesis is the prologue to the Torah,
right it's part of the tour.
the narratives are part of the Torah. Sometimes this is one of the reasons why I think it's better to just go back to calling it the Torah instead of using the word law.
Because when we hear law, we just think about commandments. Right? There's a lot of stuff beyond just commandments.
And so there are a lot of things in Genesis that, you know, I mean, starting with chapter 1 and the beginning of chapter 2, God creating the world in seven days and the whole thing with the Sabbath.
Right, and then the Sabbath commandments aren't given in
until Exodus. Right. Even though they're sort of presented
to Genesis as being built into creation. So in terms of clean and unclean animals,
there are a couple of things going on there and we're actually going to get into this more,
I'm going to answer your question. I'm not punting, but we're going to get into this more in our
next episode. We're going to particularly talk about the concept of clean and unclean in our next
episode. Okay, some depth. But to answer the question now.
with animals, the primary distinguisher between clean and unclean in terms of eating
is what we would call domesticated animals versus wild animals with a few exceptions.
Donkeys, for example, being one of those exceptions. But one of the primary, so
So, and then there are certain classes of animals like scavengers, predators that are...
unclean, right, for different, you know, you might be obvious whether unclean, right, they pray on other
scavengers eat dead bodies and dead bodies are unclean, right, so you can't eat a buzzer or a vulture, right?
And so because that is based on
something about the animal itself,
right? That means that's something that
know it could take into account. Even if you didn't necessarily see it in clean and unclean terms,
the same way Leviticus would lay it out. There are certain animals, clean animals, clean animals
could be used for sacrifices, for example, because they could be eaten. Right? So the idea is he's
taking animal more of those animals with them so that there are animals. He didn't have permission
to eat them yet, right, in general, but the offer is burn offerings, right? That kind of-
There needed to be more of those.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Well, Daniel, thank you very much for calling in and stay tuned.
We're going to in a future episode.
I think the next episode, we're going to talk a lot about more, a lot more about that
clean and unclean stuff.
So because I know there's something that people think about a lot.
So all right.
Okay.
So in this half, we're going to begin talking about some of the basic principles.
You
of what the Torah is about and talk about exactly what it means that these are fulfilled
by Christ as the new covenant.
So how does that actually work out?
Again, we don't need to reinvent the wheel.
We know how this works out.
First half, we resumed way out and just talking about the Torah as such.
hours zooming in sort of.
halfway and we're going to zoom in tighter on a few things next time. But so in these last two
halves we will only add a couple of sort of core principles that run all through the Torah
and talk about how those core principles that run through the Torah run straight through into
the New Testament and into the life of the church. Right? And then next time we'll be getting into
particular. So the first sort of core principle that we're going to talk about in this half,
right, is this idea of the Torah as a series of structures, sometimes literal structures,
sometimes more figurative that allow God to dwell safely among his people.
So we've talked before on the show about death by holiness.
The other DBH.
Yes.
That may be not cross paths.
I mean, feeling generous and charitable.
So there is this danger,
not for God, for us, for humans, for sinful humans,
presented by God's holiness.
by the holiness of God, by God's complete otherness, by His goodness, by His, and I don't know
how much I want to go down this rabbit hole. I won't go down this rabbit hole too much, but again,
as we've talked about before the show, we are talking about the divine energies here, right? So, and
And that's really how to understand this.
There's imagery used in the scripture.
Most common imagery is fire. God is a burning fire a consuming fire a fire consuming the unworthy. Yeah
But what this is getting at is for example
One of the divine energies is justice
Right meaning God is continually
eternally putting things right and putting them in order
Well, if you are a profoundly unjust person
Then for you doing
counter God putting things in order. It's going to be a painful experience. Yeah. Right.
Or God being good and therefore driving out evil. Right. If you are evil, this is going to be a
bad experience. Right. And this is what we see even when we're not talking about death by holiness.
like Isaiah comes into the presence of God, right?
And doesn't jump up and down happily.
Right say oh wow. This is so cool. I get to see God. Yeah. No, it's I'm a man of unclean lips from people of unclean lips
Like oh, I'm undone. This is not good. Yes. It's tear your clothes
It's what was me right even though he's a righteous man. Yes, he's one of the righteous and that's his experience of God right
So right that's that's what we're talking about here
And so nevertheless God loves His people and wants to live with them and among the
them and share his life with them. And so certain structures need to be put in place to allow
that to happen, in a way that will be beneficial to humanity rather than the opposite. Because
God doesn't want to inflict excruciating pain on His people all the time.
So we see this problem already laid out in Genesis, right?
Because as we were just saying...
to Daniel, right?
Genesis is the prologue to the Torah.
It's setting things up for the Torah.
And one of the things it sets up is the problems that the Torah is aimed at, right?
The rest of the Torah is going to be aimed at.
That what's given it about Sinai is aimed at.
Right from the beginning, we see this right away in Genesis chapter 3, the expulsion from paradise,
Right, Adam and Eve are cast out of paradise.
because having become sinful, having come to know evil, right?
They can no longer exist in a positive way
in the presence of God, right?
And remember, this is why God gives them mortal flesh.
This is why death comes into the world as a mercy, right?
God said, it is not good for them to live forever,
eternally
in this state knowing evil, right?
Much less that they would live eternally in that state
in the presence of God, which would be torment,
which would be hell.
Yeah, right?
Which God does not want for them.
And so he expels them, right?
From paradise, and the cherubim is put there
with the flaming sword, right?
Why is he there?
He's not there to protect God from people.
Yeah, it's not to prevent, you know,
breaking and entering.
Oh yes, it's
stop people in their simple state from trying to draw close to God.
Yeah. Right. So it is another example. This cherubim, it's another example of how God has
allowed for physical death as a means to help humanity avoid spiritual death,
which is far worse. Right. Remember, physical death is the separation of the soul from the body.
spiritual death is the separation.
of our soul from God.
Yeah, and I mean, it calls to mind, right, the thrice holy hymn where the angels sing holy, holy, holy Lord of hosts.
It's not just saying, you know, God is awesome, but it's really that sense that God is set apart as separate, is utterly different from mankind.
And so it is a praise of God, but it's also kind of a warning to a sinful creation.
Holy, you know, that's what we call it, death by holiness.
So you know, the those throne guardians, the chairman and sheriff, I'm singing that song.
It's to say this is a dangerous place.
Powerful place.
Dangerous also, you know.
So I'm not sure because I was told over and over and over and over and over and over again
that our God is an awesome God.
Oh, there it is.
So.
Wow.
Kicking at old school tonight, huh?
So moving on in Genesis.
Whew.
A lot of triggered people listening right now.
Yeah, oh yeah.
Yeah.
Sorry folks.
It's not just that they're triggered.
It's there are people out there
who are gonna have that stuck in their head all night.
That's right.
For that I apologize.
That is a big.
They hear where I'm.
None of you deserve if you listen to this show.
So moving on in Genesis, the next place we see this play out is the flood.
Right.
Preceding the flood, what does God say?
I can abide with men no longer.
Right.
You got 120 years left and then it's over.
Yeah, which doesn't mean, by the way, like, I can't take you people anymore.
Yeah, no.
It's literal.
Right.
Okay, who's present?
because they've become so evil, right?
The text says that their every thought
was always evil all the time.
Yeah.
Which, you know, I've been pretty bad
at various points in my life.
Maybe all of them, but I don't think I've ever
been quite that bad.
Have a good thought once in a while.
Not my own, right?
Comes from somewhere else, but so because humanity
has.
come to that state. God can't dwell with them anymore, and God's presence ends up destroying humanity in the flood.
Which, as we've talked about before, is basically uncreation.
And then a re-creation on the other side of it. And so God then sets his bow like a bow and arrow in
the clouds. He says, I will not make war against humanity again. And then we see in Genesis chapter 10,
the whole cycle starts.
again. Right, we get Nimrod, like the giants, we get see all of these things coming up to
the Tower of Babel. And so God is not going to destroy humanity again. And so he withdraws.
He withdraws. So his presence is no longer there. Therefore it's no longer dangerous. The
problem is, right, God withdrawing God's presence no longer being among humanity doesn't
make things better for
humanity. Yeah, right. Things are bad. They stay bad. Yeah. And so when we get to Abraham in Genesis
chapter 12, this is the beginning of the story of God drawing near to his people again.
And we aren't told, right, we were told at the flood, right, that Noah is righteous among his
generation like he's there's this one guy right to his thoughts are not
always evil all the time, right? And that's why God saves and preserves him. But we're not
told that about Abraham. We're not told about Abraham. Oh, hey, you know, there's even
though things are pretty bad, there's this one guy in the or who's who's got it all together,
right? Who's one of those Gentiles who just was doing what he was supposed to be doing,
doing even though he hadn't heard anything from God about it.
If you follow the life of Abraham, you know he needs some work.
Yeah, he has an arc, an arc of growth as a person in his, in his, what is literally described as a friendship with God.
But God comes and appears to him, right?
And this is, this is a key thing here in the Torah is that it's not that humanity repents and all becomes righteous
and God
says, okay, well now I can draw near to you again, because now it's safe.
Right. God chooses to draw near to humanity, even though we're still talking about sinful humanity.
Right. But there is still this problem that plays out. It plays out a really subtle way.
You got to really be paying attention as you read the patriarchal narratives of Abraham and Isaac
Jacob and Jacob and Joseph at the rest of Jacob's sons.
But there is this descent, there is this ongoing problem.
And one of the very subtle things that a lot of times people don't notice is
God appears in person to Abraham and comes and sits and eats with him.
Right? Appears to him over and over again.
He appears at a couple of points to Isaac.
uh... he comes and he appears to jake of a couple of times
one of those times they get a fight
Yeah.
Right.
And he gets renamed Israel.
So you go from, you know, hosting God for dinner to wrestling him to the ground.
Right.
Things are changing.
And then by the time you get, it's best.
By the time, by the time you get to Jacob's sons, God doesn't appear to any of Jacob's
sons.
Hmm. Joseph has dreams and interprets.
dreams. Yeah, so it's less. It's more distant. Right. And so God can only draw so close to
sinful humanity without it becoming dangerous. And so when God gives the Torah at Sinai, a major
element of what's going on in the Torah is going to be, okay, here's how God can now draw
close to a sinful people, live into hell among them, share his life with them, and have it be
you say for them.
Yeah, if they follow this, which they won't.
Yeah, exactly.
Yeah, like this is what you need to do, so that when God draws close to you, you don't,
you don't die.
Yes.
Yeah.
And so when I said sometimes this involves literal structures, I mean like the tabernacle.
Right.
And just to remind everybody what the tabernacle is, I think sometimes they think, you know,
it's a building.
It ain't no, it's actually not a building.
in the sense that we think of buildings.
Like it's sort of a big fence, right?
And there's a big open space in that fence.
And inside there, there's a tent, a big tent.
And inside that tent, there's a smaller tent, right?
So you've got these layers of enclosed,
enclosed in this enclosure where most people are outside.
Completely.
Yeah.
Outside the fence.
to go inside.
defense, only the priests go inside the fence if I remember correctly.
Right. There are priests and Levites inside the fence. There are priests who,
during their time of service, go into the outer tent of the tabernacle and then
the high priest, once a year, goes into the inner tent, right? The Holy of
Yeah, yeah.
One year, just the high priest, right?
And so...
there are the sort of concentric circles, right? And really the fence is not the last one.
The edge of the Israelite camp is the last one, right? Or later when we're talking about the temple,
the borders of Israel is the last one, or Judah, right? Judea, right? Is the last sort of concentric
circle? And the closer you go in within those concentric circles, the higher of a level of holiness
and purity is required of...
the human person. So this is part of why we had, well not part of why. This is the primary reason why we have
the division we were talking about in the first half between commandments given to the Israelites and
commandments given to everybody else. Is that God was not dwelling in Egypt in the tabernacle.
God was not dwelling on creed in the Tabernacle. He was not dwelling in Damascus in the Tabernacle.
He was dwelling in Israel in the Tabernacle. And so the Israelites, in that most outward
concentric circle, had to maintain this level of holiness appear to be higher than the people
of the other nations. And then the Levites and the priests who are going to go into the courtyard
Habernacle had to maintain a higher level.
They had to engage in more ritual washings.
They had to eat different foods.
The priests during the time of service when they went into the outer tent, they would
have shifts.
They would have days where they would do it.
And during those days they had to abstain from their wives.
There's a whole other.
They had to take everything to another level.
And then finally the high priest on that one day had to go to this very highest level
and had to create this.
cloud of incense so we wouldn't see God and die and had to enter with blood and
had to offer these sacrifices for his own sins first before he could even start
the rest of the ritual and on and on, right? This highest this highest level, the
closer you were going to go in, the higher level of purity someone had to maintain.
There are two main kinds of purity when we're talking about the Old Testament and
This will come up again.
next episode when we're talking about clean and unclean but those two kinds of impurity
or kinds of purity are moral purity and ceremonial purity.
Not the same thing.
Right, not the same thing.
And if you don't understand that these are different things, you will not understand the
Torah at all.
So if you became morally impure...
Right. You were also ceremonially and ceremonially impure.
Yeah. Meaning you murder someone.
Right. You are now morally impure.
You are also ceremonially impure, meaning you can't, you don't need to be going
into the tabernacle after you murder somebody.
That'll have a bad result.
Yeah. If you try to draw close to God, right?
Immediately.
Right. Without purifying.
Perfect.
And ceremonial impurity is
about not being ready to go into the tabernacle or in some cases near it, right?
Right.
To whatever level you were allowed.
Yeah.
And there were things that could make you ceremonially, ceremonially easy for me to say impure that
were not moral impurities.
So like touching a Torah scroll or touching a dead body going to the bathroom.
These were things that made you ceremonial and pure.
So you couldn't, you know, you couldn't go into the tabernacle.
Until the wash didn't wear purified, right?
Yeah, you had to be purified first, but these are not moral impurities.
It's not a sin to touch his horoscope.
It's not a sin to bury your dead grandfather, right?
Yeah.
But in fact, quite the opposite.
Some of the things that works.
We're seeing as the greatest good works, right, from the perspective of the Torah, were
things that
required a person to contract ceremonial impurity on behalf of someone else.
So if you want to example Tobit in the book of Tobit, right? The great good thing he does before
God is he goes and he buries the dead who have been left unburied while doing that requires you
to touch and handle dead bodies.
So, so, unclean does not equal sinful.
Bad.
Right. And in fact, being willing to do that, meaning you're not going to be able to enjoy the full communion
right of the rest of the people and with God for a time until you're purified,
being willing to do that for the sake of helping someone is seen as this great, great good thing you could do.
This is in the background of the parable of the Good Samaritan.
This is why the priest and the Levite passed by on the other side of the road.
Because they're more...
concerned about preserving their own ceremonial purity than they are about helping someone in need because that person is bloody and beaten.
Whereas the Samaritan is already by virtue of being a Samaritan ceremonially unclean.
Right, and so he goes and he helps.
Right, he goes the up. This is in the background there. Right. And, and this dynamic.
this dynamic of being willing to become unclean for the sake of someone else is also something
that's going on and I'm not going to elaborate on this right now just because it's a whole
other thing but elsewhere at some point we'll discuss this more. This is part of what's
going on in the understanding of Christ's incarnation as a descent for our sex.
But we'll get into that.
But so, yeah, ceremonial purity, not sin, right?
Even though sin also makes you ceremonially impure.
Right.
One causes the other, but the other doesn't cause the one.
And we're going to be focusing in more on moral purity and sin in the third half coming
up here.
so
There may be some folks who think well, okay, yeah, but right we don't have the tabernacle or the temple anymore
Right so that's that's all gone now
So I guess this just sort of doesn't apply now. This is one of those things right ceremonial law
We could just toss
Toss all that stuff out related to the temple because
God's presence isn't just in this one
Place with concentric circles around it and stuff and all that and I say to you not so fast
Because that's not what the New Testament does with this principle.
No, I mean, number one, there are washings.
Yeah, we see in the New Testament and washings that we see in liturgical practice of the
Sure, yes.
Right, right.
And on the other side of those wash.
is entering in to a holy place to do a holy thing. Yes. And
Rember Matthew 5, right? It's not even that this is relaxed.
It's not even that these commandments are relaxed. In fact, if anything,
they're heightened in a certain way. Yeah. Right? Because the presence of God
doesn't go from being in that one look
cow, right, within that one tent or that one building, to being everywhere and or nowhere,
right? But according to the book of Acts, right, that presence of God, the Holy Spirit
comes to dwell in each human, right, who is baptized and receives the Holy Spirit.
Yeah. And this is demonstrated at Pentecost, right? And when you look at Pentecost, you need
remember how the prison
of God descends into the Tabernacle and the First Temple. This is what it's doing. It is descending
again now, but now it's in the church. That's what happens at Pentecost and Acts.
Right. It's in people. Like Soil in Green, the Temple is now people.
When not like soyling cream.
Not snow, yeah.
Like green or like green day.
Yeah.
I don't even know what that metaphor be.
But okay.
I get you try to do a band reference.
I'll acknowledge.
You don't know that Green Day is actually named
after a banner in that film that says,
Soilant Green Day?
Oh no, I didn't know that.
I actually learned something today.
Hey, I got one, everybody write it down.
I knew a pop culture reference and fun, Steve.
I'll have to go back and watch it.
I rewatched it a couple of years ago with Charlton.
I'm a Charlton Heston thing.
I watched Soilant Green.
I watched Omega Man.
Watch.
like a whole bunch of them.
Ooh, go back again.
Any plans in there?
Omega man is, I continuously watch Planet of the Apes movies.
I can't wait.
There's the new one coming out that looks amazing.
Um, nice.
But uh, um, oh yeah, Omega man by the way, worst adaptation of Richard Mathisons, I am
legend ever.
the three. The one that's actually closest to the to the book is last man on
Earth starring Vincent Price.
Second is Will Smith's I Am Legend with the original ending that you get as a
bonus feature. Then that movie with the theatrical ending then Omega man. Omega man
not even really in the right it's you know I was gonna say it had
the same title but it doesn't even have the same title. It's like vaguely related. Even
though it says based upon in the credits. But anyway, enough of I am legend. But so I
think a lot of times when we look at the day of Pentecost, right, and we celebrate the
day of Pentecost. We don't see that that sense of danger has been maintained.
should be maintained. I've never heard it a baptism. Right? Okay, now the Holy Spirit is going to come
up on this person and they are in grave danger. Right? No one does that. But the scriptures do go out
out of their way to point that out.
Because there's this pattern, right,
that St. Luke follows in at the...
end of Luke in the beginning of Acts, which is a pattern he's getting out of Leviticus.
So if there's a tertiary takeaway from tonight's episode, it's Go Read Leviticus, everybody.
But so in Leviticus, they build the tabernacle.
They purify the tabernacle and all that's accoutrements with blood.
And then the President...
of God comes down and fills the Tabernacle, right? The Holy Spirit fills the Tabernacle.
And then in the next chapter after the presence of God comes and fills the Tabernacle,
Aaron's near-to-well sons, Nehda B and Abahu, go in drunk to offer strange fire at the wrong time
in terms of incense in the tabernacle and fire comes out and
kills them. This is the first instance in the scriptures of someone being on fire with the Holy Spirit.
We use that term differently now. That's part of my point. It's Lori not to denote danger.
Right. And so St. Luke, right, because they get all of the New Testament authors assume that their
their readers are.
thoroughly familiar with the Torah. They assume it. Right? And this is part of our problem in
reading and interpreting the New Testament well is that we by and large aren't. Right?
Because he does this very subtly, but St. Luke's Gospel ends with the Christians, the disciples,
all continuously in the temple praising God.
Have you ever noticed that?
Yeah.
And then you go over to the beginning of Acts,
and they're hiding in a room.
Yeah.
Waiting for the Holy Spirit.
Yep.
Have a strike, anybody is odd?
Right.
That's...
So...
Right.
What was just before that?
What was just before that was the story about the road to Emmaus.
Right?
Emmaus being the climactic battle of the Macapeean revolt.
You can read about this.
and first Maccabees, after which they rededicated the temple.
Right? So the idea that, say, Luke is telegraphing by that ending to his gospel is
the rededication of the temple is coming and it has to do with the temple being filled with
Christians. Right? So he's teasing it, teasing volume two. So when we get into volume two,
We have the
Christians, they have been purified by the blood of Christ through his death. And now the presence
of God in the Holy Spirit descends upon them and fills them. And then what happens afterwards?
We get this story about Ananias and Safaira, two people again. Who come to the apostles,
who come to the church who come to the people who are filled with the Holy Spirit.
And they lie and say Peter says you have lied to God you have lied to the Holy Spirit
That what happens they fall over dead and people carry them out just like they dab in abu
Right so St. Luke uses that pattern to very deliberately communicate oh no no no no no no
This is still a dangerous thing
The presence of God in us is still a dangerous thing
And this becomes the basis for everything St. Paul is going to say about in various places,
about our body being a temple of the Holy Spirit, and the Holy Spirit dwelling with us,
and within it's not quenching the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, it's not just like a neat, beautiful little metaphor.
It's really about, well, how do you treat the temple?
How do you treat the Tavaernacle?
What are you supposed to be doing?
Right.
This is
why he has this, he's not just a prude. This is why he has this emphasis on sexual immorality.
And precisely this context of our body being a temple, the Holy Spirit.
Yeah. Exactly. And being defiled. And so this principle, now we've seen, right,
we did it as kind of a quick run through, but we did this kind of quick run through of this
from the Torah, right? And then into the New Testament.
right? And so there's a lens, there's a fraction point there. As we move from the
Torah to the New Testament, where something shifts, how would we describe that
shift? I would describe that shift as a move from external to internal.
Right? So the Israelites are given this structure, external to them, right? You
You have to go to the tabernacle, and you can only go so close.
right, or you have to go to the temple. It is external. It may be far away, right?
But through the way you approach, like literally physically approach, this literal physical
sanctuary, right, and the way you treat it and the purity and the holiness that you have to maintain.
This is sort of preparatory to understanding what it's going to mean to have.
the Spirit of God, God Himself, come in dwell in your heart.
And what that means in terms of the holiness, the purity, that has to be maintained,
the dedication that has to be maintained of yourself now, of yourself, not just of
of a building over there.
Yeah.
And this also gives us an image that refraction point
that lends.
Give.
This is a better idea of what Saint Paul means, for example, when he says that the Torah was a teacher.
It gave this external thing as a way to help humanity understand this spiritual internal thing,
so that we would be prepared for the fullness that comes in Christ.
All right, well, we're going to go ahead and go to earth.
second break and we'll be right back with the third half of the Lord of
Spirits. Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a
moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits. Give them a
call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
The
Ancient Bates Lampstown Institute is an introductory media training for
for Orthodox Christians aged 18 to 23,
who are interested in learning skills in digital media
and applying them to the service of the church.
At Lampstand, a group of 10 students
will gather to learn the essentials
of podcasting and video production,
and the why and how of Orthodox media ministry.
Students will execute their own digital media projects
under the direction of ancient faith staff and network.
Upon the program's conclusion, participants will lead
with foundational ministry experience.
Technical links.
creative skills and career mentors.
The weekend will include sessions on podcasting,
audio production, live radio, video making,
marketing and media ministry.
Plus open work sessions for recording radio material,
refining a personal project,
and preparing a live radio broadcast.
The institute will take place
at the Ancient Faith Ministries headquarters
in Chesterton, Indiana on July 18th through the 21st,
2024 programming will begin Thursday, July 18th
at 6.30 p.m.
and conclude with Divine Liturgy and Lunch on Sunday morning.
For more information and to apply, please visit ancientfaith.com.
That's ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-234.
That's 855 AF radio.
Welcome back.
So I should say, you know, they're at the end of the second half.
I had someone dispute my claims about the origins of the band's name for Green Day.
And said that it has to do with a certain plant that people like to put inside pipes and cigarettes and so forth.
but I will say
having done some very fast research on the interwebs during the break that this is a contested issue.
So I am going to stick with the ancient legends that were given to me in the elder days.
But yes, it is a thing. It is a thing both ways. Yeah, the marijuana thing, I mean,
that's just not anywhere near as interesting as Tuesday is sort of like Green Day,
as it says on on us.
signs in the film. So just throwing that one out there. I'm happy to have to consider for my own
purposes, the way in which the weed explanation fits into my all rock songs are actually about heroin theory.
Every single one of them. I do not have the time to listen to you wine.
About nothing and everything all at once. Yes, exactly. At the end of this episode, we'll say I hope
hope you had it.
time we prefer life. Anyway, so we actually do have a caller on the line who's probably
just getting irritated and annoyed at listening to us go on about this stuff. So we're going
to go ahead and talk to Avery. So Avery, welcome to the Lurda Spirit's podcast. What is on your mind?
Probably blessed. God bless you. Thank you. I will say I just finished my main line of
Lord of Fear is podcasting starting in September and ending now.
And I'm glad I was able to...
to call in before the impending end of the show.
So I'm very happy about that.
I did have a question about, I know you've talked about how the Gentiles fulfilled a 10
tribe, the lost tribes of Israel, but my question is how do the two remaining tribes fit into
Christianity and then how do they operate with the Torah and that
All right, that's nice and clear.
I'm gonna go ahead and punt it directly to you, Father.
Yes.
So, because I know you have something to say about this.
This is one of the most controversial things I ever say.
And since I'm longing for cancellation,
I love an opportunity to say it as publicly as possible.
So if we're talking about individual Jewish people
converting to Orthodox Christianity, right?
There's a fundamental problem with the idea that they would fully keep Torah in that to really keep Torah fully you have to keep it in community.
So this is a practical issue, right? Like if I have a Jewish person come and join my parish, right? And if I were to say to them, okay, you need to keep kosher because you're Jewish, that would just be he couldn't eat with the rest of us.
Right. That would be excluding him from our community. Right. So that is that is not a burden that the
church places on individual converts like that. And I don't think that that's the controversial part.
Here's the controversial part. I think as I hope and pray will one day happen, and I'm going to talk
about this more in my concluding comments, that one day we will have a mass conversion of Jewish
which people enter in the Orthodox Church.
The day that I think would be wonderful would be the day that the Patriarchate of Jerusalem is just so overwhelmed
by Jewish converts, including the high rabbit that we end up with a Jewish patriarch of Jerusalem again for the first time in 1970 years.
And if that happens by God's grace, and we have whole...
church as a communities of Jewish Christians, then I would expect that that Jewish church,
just like the Greek church or the Russian church or any other church of a people and a
nation, would keep their own ways. And I suspect that such a church would keep Torah in
away more reminiscent of the Jewish Christians of the first century.
Wow, that would be amazing wouldn't it?
Yes.
I mean, we're seeing here speculating a bunch of Gentiles on microphones.
So, yeah.
Yes.
Well, I would have come up more on that at the end here.
I think there are things we could do to help that along.
Oh, yeah, absolutely.
If we really want to see that happen.
Yeah.
Well, thank you.
I do want to say quickly that this podcast has not only changed my faith, but it's really
changed the way I...
community and hopefully it's working in a way to change nothing it's bad but
the way my pair of shoes community and gathered so I do thank you for that
thank you Avery thanks for listening thank you all right I have to admit go
ahead for a second there I dared hope that that was going to be Avery Brooks I'm
pretty sure it wasn't yeah I mean that is a hundred percent of the voice yeah it's a
please.
distinctive voice. Yeah, he didn't ask about flying cars once. So yeah, yeah, yeah.
That's the big question I associate with Avery Brooks is where are the flying cars?
Yeah. Okay, I like I personally really liked the interview he did with William
Shatter where he just sat there and blinked around on a piano for half the day. Yes,
Yes, fascinating.
William Schatner, who has probably been on more documents.
films than any other human who has ever lived.
Yes.
Yeah.
Agreed.
Okay.
All right.
First half, we talked about Torah in general and how it relates to the church.
Second half, we started to zoom in and we talked about one of the core principles of the
Torah, which is how to live in such a way as to be compatible with the presence of God
so that we don't have to suffer DBH, death by holiness, that is.
And the third half, we're going to zoom in a little more.
So what's on the menu now?
Yes.
So now we're zooming in a little more on moral impurity,
specifically, sin, to put a finer point on it.
And the way in which the Torah functions
as a sin management system.
Right.
So to start with, we have to make sure we're keyed in on our correct understanding of what
sin is.
Because I know for a lot of us, based on cultural things, sin is breaking a rule, specifically
one of God's rules.
And then God is mad, or God has to punish it, or however you view that.
But that's not...
not how the Torah sees sin.
We'll just start with that.
That's not how the Torah presents sin.
And there are sort of two valences, I guess,
in terms of how sin is presented to the Torah.
The first is sin is described as sort of like a biological entity,
meaning like a bacteria or a virus.
like a disease.
Now, of course, they didn't have the idea of bacteria or viruses at that time in history,
but they saw diseases, right, and how diseases worked and how they spread, right, and how
they brought about death if not treated and not dealt with.
And so sin is portrayed very much in that sense, right.
But there is sort of a reality to it, right?
And the ways of dealing with sin and moral impurity
are very closely related to the way that disease
was dealt with, things like quarantine.
Like you have to set the center is separated
until he can be purified by various means.
He's separated from the tabernacle, from other people.
And then that purification and healing is required.
And we've mentioned before,
it was way back in the long ago time.
I won't even guess which episode.
It's a dim memory fading off into the sunset,
because I'm an old man.
But we talked about Christ's healings
in relation to this at one point, right?
That one of the reasons why Christ performing all
of these healings of physical disease.
is so prominent in the Gospels is that this is an image of healing forgiveness restoration
from sin. And often in the story of Christ's healing, these two things are tied together,
right? Which is easier to say to this paralyzed man. Your sins are forgiven or rise up and walk,
right? And so the physical healing and the forgiveness of sins is sort of tied together
in this way, sometimes very explicitly.
And that's related to this understanding of sin.
And then, relatedly, this isn't really another concept, it's more of another valence
or another sort of slightly to the side perspective, that sin leaves a kind of metaphysical
taint.
It leaves a kind of stain or a spore in the world and in people and on people and on even
physical objects.
Yeah, places.
Let's get TANED.
Right?
I was I was a Sam just been reading the the edifice literature from ancient Greek mythology and and stuff and and you know if you guys know about the life of edipists, you know, he was pretty messed up.
But yeah, I mean he shows up like an edipist at colonists, which is one of the plays by Sophocles.
He shows up and people like get out of here. You know like this guy is cursed by the gods
You know get out you know and that's exactly this idea that there's this sort of evil that messes up places
by an evil person or a cursed person, just being around.
Yeah, yeah.
And of course, first example of this in scripture
is Genesis 3 when Adam is told,
curse it is the ground because of you.
Right.
What Adam has done is not just going to affect him
or his relationship with God,
but it's gonna affect the ground that he has to work
to get his food from.
So there's gonna be thorns and thistles and effort, right?
So there's...
this taint left. And of course, this is, you know, the day of atonement ritual, the blood
that's taken into sanctuary is used to purify the physical objects, right? The arc of the
covenant, the altar of insects, right? The physical objects in there, not people.
Yeah. What did they ever do? But nothing. But it's the sin that kind of got on them, so to
speak. But the language is you have to go in and aton for the altar, right? It has to
be pure.
again with blood from and of course that's done in the sanctuary because that's the place where it's most dangerous because that's where God is
When you're when you're outside the camp, right
Sin still a problem and sin is still sin, right?
But that that residue that stain that tape doesn't it doesn't present the same danger, right as it does
the closer you are to the the presence of God and
And so the use
In which this is dealt with, in addition to that quarantine ideas, that once the person is quarantined and separated, the way that you deal with the sin, the disease, right?
And its residual is through the cycle of daily sacrifices, the daily sin offerings.
And then as we just mentioned the annual day of atonement, ritual, which not only takes away the sin of the people, right?
And again, here.
sin has this metaphysical reality to it because you can take it and you can put it on a goat
and the goat can carry it away. Yeah. Right. And that's a lot more on that everybody.
They're checking out our episode called the Beast shall make a tonement. We go to
incredible detail in that. Yeah, but that's a very particular way of seeing sin, right? You can't
take a series of rule violations and put it somewhere.
Right.
And so
But in addition to, in tandem with that cycle of daily sin offerings and the annual day of
atonement, there is also what we today, thanks to Latin, call penance. There was restitution.
There was repentance, the consistent of concrete actions that had to also be done.
Right so if I go and I steal something from
my neighbor, I go and steal money from my neighbor, I can't just go and partake of that
day sin offering and be like, cool, we're all good.
Right?
I have the Torah prescribes.
Okay, here's how you do that.
I have to go and pay back five times what I stole.
Then go participate.
Yeah.
Make it right.
In the sacrifice.
And then I am right healed that I am restored.
Right? See Psalm 50, Psalm 51, if you're not using the Orthodox study level. Right?
With David, then shall I offer Bullocks on that altar? Yeah. Right? Not sacrifices
aren't important at all. God doesn't care about the blood of bulls and goats. Right?
It's that God doesn't just want that. I'm not gonna bribe him with that. He
wants me to have a broken in a contract. Hard about what I've done. And then once
Once I've been restored, then I go and offer.
the books, right? Then I go in off of the sacrifices. Right? And so one of the things that's very
commonly misinterpreted. And it's weird. Let me say this, it's weird because this is an idea. I only
encountered relatively recently. Like within the last 10 years, I've been studying the Bible for a
a lot more than 10 years.
But our last 10 years, I've been running into this idea over and over and over and over
again among certain old testament scholars, only certain ones.
And I don't even have a good idea of what connects them to give me an idea of why they might
be reading this this way.
But there's this idea now that people put forward that sacrifices in the Old Testament couldn't
Deal with voluntary sins.
The sacrifices the daily sin offerings of the day of atonement only dealt with involuntary sins but
But I mean there's there's explicit things in there of that you can't like accidentally
Do yeah, well, that's the thing that's it so just so people know right what we talk about voluntary and involuntary
sins
What we usually mean is that?
that if I throw a rocket someone's head and it hits them in
kills them. That was the voluntary sin. If I throw a rock over a fence and I don't realize
there's a person there and the rock hits them and kills them, that's an involuntary sin.
Yeah. Right. Meaning I had no intent to sin whatsoever. I was just negligent in some way
or careless or incoherstous, right?
And so, yeah, even though people say that...
all the time not not everybody but a certain group of people says this over and over and over again
like it's just a fact. It doesn't really make sense when you read the Torah because like how do I
involuntarily steal? Yeah. Right? Like if I if I steal from my neighbor deliberately like there's
no way to a tone for it. Right. I'm just done. That's like if I accidentally steal something
I have to pay back five times.
Yeah, it's like no, it's like when you accidentally pocket a pen at the bank
Right, like then I guess I have to go and give the bank five pens. Five pens. Yeah, but if I deliberately steal the pen
There is no forgiveness for me, right?
That doesn't seem to be what the text is saying no
Right, it just doesn't seem to be what the text is saying to me. I don't understand how that's tenable
Right, and I don't understand how there would have been any Israelites left
right after a relatively
short period of time. Right? Because all you would have to do is commit one voluntary sin
and you're done because there's no forgiveness for you. There's no way to be reconciled
according to this view. And, you know, David. Yeah. Just, you know, there are lots of
people, the old testament who commit voluntary sins and yet somehow are reconciled and offer
sacrifices. Yeah that's yeah so it just
It doesn't work.
And I'm not sure because a lot of these people are like smart.
Very intelligent people and well educated.
And I respect them, but I don't know where they've gotten this idea
or how they think that works.
What you actually see in the Torah and the place to look for this
is in everybody's favorite book of the Bible,
the Book of Numbers.
Once you're done with reading Leviticus, read numbers.
Yes.
I've had a challenge or something like a nice bucket challenge.
I was told you could not be math.
Yes.
So, numbers chapter 50.
By the way, people, if you haven't read numbers or you haven't read in a while, it's
not just a bunch of senses taking.
There is some narrative in this.
Not just numbers despite the name.
Yes, right.
Yes.
So, numbers chapter 15 verses 30 and 31.
But the person who does anything with a high hand.
whether he is native or a sojourner, reviles the Lord. And that person shall be cut off from
among his people. Because he is despised the word of the Lord and has broken his commandment,
that person shall be utterly cut off. His iniquity shall be on him. So what's that high hand
thing? Is that like someone waving, hey, look at me, look at me. Right. Well, so this can't mean,
again, voluntary sin. Yeah, because the punishment for this.
is being cut off from the people, meaning death or exile.
Right.
And the Torah doesn't commit the death penalty for everything.
That's clearly you can eat an owl and not get the death penalty.
Okay.
There's a lot of owl eating.
Like to examples.
Owl eating.
Yeah.
I know.
The owl eating episode.
Someone asked in the YouTube discussion whether we had already passed owl fair week.
So afraid so.
Yep.
No, I'll's for you.
Now I'm to petrified someone's gonna show up with like some kind of bookdowell at
Pasta and I'm in Pajan country so
Somebody catches an owl. They're gonna cook it up, but on the other hand
It'll probably be delicious. Yeah, I mean I would read to admit it. Yeah
Yeah, that's.
But so the right, you don't get the death penalty or exile for
And again, if you did, there would not be any Israelites for very long, right?
So this time, that's something else.
What does it mean to hold your hand up high?
What is that referring to? That's referring to taking an oath.
Yeah. So in other words, I'm committed to this.
Right. Right. And so this isn't deliberate sin.
This is unrepentance.
So it's not that it's deliberate before the fact, which most sin is.
It's that it's unrepentant after the fact, which an unfortunate amount of sin is.
Right.
So the idea is, right, yeah, I did it.
Yeah, right.
I'm going to keep doing it.
Yeah.
Keep doing it. There's nothing wrong with it.
Right.
And if you think about that for a second.
And think about some of the people, again, in the Torah, who suffer being cut off from
among the people.
Right?
And this describes them.
Think about Korah.
Hmm.
Right?
Why is he going to be the high priest?
He's no better than me.
Yeah, that's what he said.
I should be a priest too.
Right?
Think about Eiken and Joshua.
Not only does he take the gold and the treasure and he hides it, but when it's found out that
someone has it, and so the wrath of God is upon all the people, he doesn't repent.
He doesn't mess up.
He doesn't confess what he did.
Right?
They have to go find it.
He's unrepentant.
He gets cut off from among the people.
So this not only makes sense is just a reading of this text, but it makes sense of the Torah.
Right now it fits into the...
rest of the Torah, the rest of the Old Testament, how it was practiced. But notice that this
fact, we're told as that passage in numbers continues for this kind of person, for this
high-handed person, who sins with a handheld eye, this person who is unrepentant, you can't
offer any sacrifices for them. Right, you can't offer sacrifices this guy because
He's not repent.
So there's not going to be forgiveness.
There's not going to be healing if he's unrepentant.
It doesn't matter how many bulls and goats you offer to God, right?
The guy's unrepentant.
This is related to what St. John is talking about in 1 John when he talks about the person
who sins unto death who you shouldn't pray for.
Right?
It's the same kind of idea.
This is the sinner who is not repenting.
Right?
If someone is sinning completely unrepentantly and I pray for God to forgive those sins,
that they haven't repented of,
God is not going to forgive those sins
until and unless they repent.
Now I can pray to God and ask God
that he will do something to move them to repentance.
That's different, right?
That he will and bless them and do other things for them, right?
But God isn't going to forgive someone's sins
that they aren't repenting of.
Yeah, and I think this is important to underline that
there is a difference between being a sinner and being an unrepentant sinner. And I think a lot of
errors are committed when people just collapse those things into the same thing.
You know, I've heard it said one time and I believe this very much, that it's not sin that keeps
us out of the kingdom of God. It's lack of repentance that keeps us out of the kingdom of God.
It's raw sinners, raw sinners.
But if we don't repent, that's where we have the problem.
Right.
And there are a lot of people who we think of as sinners, right?
Who we think of as the bad people.
Maybe who are doing horrible things to themselves and even other people.
But the reality is, these are people who are deeply lost and literally from their perspective
struggling to survive every
day. And what they need is not to be sort of vilified and identified as sinners, but what
they need is they need the way out presented to them, the way out of repentance, right,
but that is possible and that healing is possible, right? Because even though they look on
repentance to us in the sense that they're not changing, and they may be justifying horrible
things that they do.
Because from their perspective, they have to do those things to survive, right?
And we interpret that as unrepentance.
Right? But in a lot of cases, it's because they don't know or think repentance
transformation healing is actually possible for them.
Yeah, and God knows
whether they are repentant, or even trying to be.
But so the fact that
right? The sacrificial system of the of the Torah. The
fact that you can have this problem, right, of, well, we're doing the
sacrifices, but people aren't repenting. And so the purpose, the
ostensible purpose of those sacrifices in terms of reconciliation and healing
and restoration, isn't working because the people aren't repenting points to a
certain problem of externality, right? The fact that sort of like we saw
So
the sanctuary, the actual offering of an animal and the eating of the parts of the animal
is this thing external to people. That was intended to help teach them about repentance.
And transformation. And so this is another place where we see that lens we talked about in the last
half of something moving.
from external to internal.
And when we say there's this move to internal, we don't mean that forgiveness is purely an internal thing.
Like I go, I say, I'm sorry to God, I'm healed from it internally in some, in some way, right?
Because repent, the repentance part is still accomplished externally.
Yeah, you can't just say, well, I said I was sorry.
Yeah, even if you say it like in a hard
way. Like, okay, you're sorry. Now make it right. Right. So there's confessing sin, there's
correcting, becoming faithful to God, ceasing from repeating to do it. There's making restitution,
healing and restoring the damage you've done to yourself and other people through that sin. Right.
But what we don't have anymore is that purely external
offering of animals. Right. And also when we say that it's internalized, we're not saying
that this was purely external in the Torah. And here's what I mean by that. Sometimes people
will read what Jesus says when he's teaching Torah in the Gospels as, oh well Christ is
Cranking this up.
and making it more severe. Right. Right. You know, it used to be just you couldn't commit adultery,
but then Christ says, if you look at a woman with lust in your heart, that's just as bad. See,
so he's ratcheting it up. Right. I hate to tell you or I hate to break it to you, but in the Torah,
it was already bad to lust after women in your heart.
That's not something new that Jesus is at it.
you know, especially I chose that example because you know, there's the commandment, do not commit adultery.
There's also that whole thing about not coveting your neighbor's wife.
There it is.
That's in the top 10 by the way everybody.
Yes, right. Like that's in there, right.
And this is, you know, folks read Deuteronomy. See now, now I'm going to have you read the whole Torah.
We got Leviticus numbers Deuteronomy.
Read Deuteronomy. Deuteronomy over and over again.
It's like, yes, your circumcised in the flesh is your heart circumcised.
That's not some later metaphorical thing, like, oh, circumcision was literal.
But then later we talk about it metaphorically.
That's right there at the Torah, the same Torah that talks about physical circumcision,
talks about circumcision of the heart.
Right.
What Christ is doing is he's re-internalizing it.
Because that danger of externality had really set in.
You get to the point the prophets where God tells Israel stop offering the sacrifices.
You honor me with your lips, but your heart is far from me.
You aren't repentant.
Stop killing the goats.
Let the goats live.
Right?
Because it's not fulfilling any purpose because you're not repentant.
This is one of those things that Jesus is always going
after the Pharisees about.
is about what they're super concerned about and what they're less concerned about.
For example, you tie the mint and dill and cumin. You go to your little spice garden,
and you cut out 10% of these little herbs in your herb garden so that you can tie
then make sure you give 10% of everything. He says, how about like justice?
Yes.
Are you particular about that?
Just a smursey faith, like love.
Yeah, compassion, right?
Are you so deliberate about that as you are about, you know,
tithing from your herb garden?
Notice though what Jesus says.
He said, these things you should have done while not neglecting the others also.
He doesn't say don't worry about tithing from your herbs.
Right?
He says you should be.
just as concerned about keeping these very important internal commands and
demands of the Torah as you are about these external ones. So that said as we
move into the New Testament, the sin offerings and the day of Atoma get
taken up in Christ's
sacrifice because Christ sacrifice and acts this cosmic day of atonement which was spoken of in various pieces of
Second Temple Jewish literature, Second Enic is a good example. This cosmic day of atonement meaning atonement for the
cosmos for the creation. The whole creation is purified by the blood of Christ from the Rizid Jum of sin, right?
the taking away
sin that happens. Right? Christ's own offering of himself to the Father is a
sacrifice. And so now the climax of our repentance as God's people is not going
in participating in the daily sin offering and not participating in an
annual once a year day of atonement, the climax of our repentance is
is now participating in the Eucharist,
which is a participation in Christ's sacrifice.
Yeah, so I mean that the pattern is the same
and the climax in a sense is the same
in that it is about communion with God,
but now instead of the temporary animal sacrifices,
it is the sacrifice of Christ himself.
The meal has gotten much higher, as high as possible,
Cause we're playing the very-
body and blood of God himself.
Right. And we still have a type of quarantine.
There are times when we've committed certain types of sin, right?
Where we have to separate ourselves.
From the Eucharist, from the community, the repentance needs to happen.
The healing and the transformation needs to happen.
And then that
culminates in receiving the Eucharist again.
It is the same principle from the Torah at play.
And notice that it's not just the Eucharist.
I mean, here's the Eucharist.
We receive the Eucharist for a mission of sins.
But there are a number of sacraments that bring with them
forgiveness.
I have solution obviously, right after confession, but holy
function, the anointing with oil, right?
St. James says, gather the presbyters, right?
Gather the priests, right?
They'll annoy him.
Pray for him.
He will be healed.
His sins will be forgiven, right?
Right there again, physical healing tied together with, with
the forgiveness of sins, baptism is for the remission of
sins.
Right.
and that all makes...
makes sense if we understand, again, what healing is, if sin is a disease that leaves a
taint and a spore, right, then forgiveness of sin is reconciliation, healing, restoration,
purification, cleansing, right?
And a restoration of right relationships between us and God and between us and other people.
So of course...
all of the sacraments, all of the ways in which we receive God's grace, all the ways in which God
works in our life, brings with us healing, restoration, reconciliation, right? And so all of them bring
in that sense forgiveness in one way or the other.
Yep.
All right.
Well, we've reached.
the end of our third half now. And surprise, surprise everybody, this is not the last episode
of the podcast. Although when there's another episode, this will be the last, as we said earlier,
anyway, we can't do that joke too many times. Anyway, so that is the good thing about
Cicifist jokes, though, is that you can tell them over and over again. That is. And they get
funnier each time. That is true. Yeah so next time we will continue more on some of these
themes. So there will be another episode in a couple of weeks. But just to try to wrap up this one,
you know, I said earlier, but I think it's worth bringing this thought back around because it's
it's difficult when you've been raised to think that there's these sort of very just
almost discrete stages, you know, where there's this Judaism thing in the Old Testament,
and then there's this Christianity thing in the New Testament.
right, which is definitely the way that I was raised. I was raised in contexts that were
very much shaped by dispensationalism. And I think that a lot of Christians in America,
even if they're not part of a dispensationalist group, have this sense in one way or another.
And so the theme that I wanted to reiterate is the idea that there's not this religion
in the old testament and then there's
a separate, different new religion in the New Testament.
That it's simply one.
And I thought this was very beautifully expressed in what your grandfather at the beginning
of your book, The Religion of the Apostles, where you start out with a question, was St.
Paul a convert?
There's a certain sense in which the answer to that question is, yes, he converts to Jesus
Christ, for sure, who speaks to him directly.
Does he can...
from one religion to another. No, absolutely not. Jesus didn't found a new religion.
Right? It is simply that, St. Paul realized, wait a minute, my hope as a Pharisee is coming to fruition
right now. It's coming to fruition. I didn't realize that it was happening right now.
You know, he realized, wait a minute, I'm at a different point on the timeline that I've always
believed in.
that time of fulfillment had come, that the Messiah had come.
Because you can't really believe that Christianity is a new religion,
and also say that Jesus is the Messiah.
We talked about a little bit this a bit.
And was it the previous episode or two before?
I'm blanking now.
But you know, the one that we talked about,
Jesus is the Christ, the Son of the Living God.
You can't say that he's the Messiah and also say that he's started some new religion,
because calling him the Messiah means that he fits into this existing story that has been
being told all this time.
And so to say that there's this new story and that we don't need to pay attention to
what's been being told contradicts that very idea.
as the Messiah means he's the Messiah of Israel.
It means that the church is Israel.
This is very much a big paradigm shift if you're not used to thinking this way.
And I don't mean to say, oh, Christians don't like to read the Old Testament or although
I'm sure that's true for a lot of them.
But to say that that means actually that we have to take the actual content of the Old
Testament itself very seriously.
You can't just look at it as being sort of a long prolog that now the
prologues over and now we've got kind of the real story.
No, it was leading up to Christ and our eyes are fixed on Christ, but to understand who
Christ is, we need to know the Torah and the rest of the Old Testament, but especially
the Torah.
why he's the one who gave it. He's the one who spoke to Moses on
Sinai, it came from him, right? He's the logiver. Moses receives the law from him, but he's
the logiver. He's the Torah giver, right, to use the more precise language. And when we begin to
take the Old Testament, especially the Torah much more seriously, number one, it means we're going
to read it a lot more which I very much recommend everybody does.
especially in the Orthodox Churchless face it, a lot of ignorance about just the contents
of the Old Testament.
To see nothing about how to understand it, but just the contents.
Like, who are the characters?
What are the stories?
There's a lot of ignorance about that within the Orthodox Church, and certainly I know
that in other groups as well that can often be true.
But also that as we read it and begin to understand.
better than I think what it does is it
vivifies our experience of being Christians.
We see how deep the roots go.
We see where we are in the story.
Right, there's something profoundly kind of
unhistorical about trying to ignore or marginalize
or even reject the Old Testament.
People say, oh, well, that was the Old Testament.
We're in the new one now.
No, no, that's not what-
what that means. As Orthodox Christians, we are profoundly historical people. And by
that I don't know, just mean that our church is really old. I mean that it is rooted from
Genesis 1. And you can't uproot it. You can't say, well, I've got the flower. So, you know,
the rest who cares, that's not how this works. That's not how this works. It's all connected.
all
one thing, it is the same God, it is the same Lord the whole way through. And I know that there are
parts of the Old Testament that can be difficult to understand. You know, we joke about that a little
bit sometimes. Leviticus and numbers, especially, can be difficult for people and Joshua's another one
and I can be really difficult and so forth, but this is
worth wrestling with, you know, his grownups, we've got all got things in our lives that
we wrestle with that we know it's worth it. I wrestle with this because it's worth it,
because this needs to be part of who I am. I need to be part of this. This is really
worth it. And I think a lot of times people won't wrestle with what's in the old testimony
because they don't actually think it's worth it. It is worth it. The apostles wrestle with
the old testament in the
their lives and their writings.
The Holy Fathers that follow them do
are the divine services of the church
are constantly engaging with what's in the Old Testament,
constantly.
And, you know, if you're looking for a place
where that's true, you know,
come to the services next week,
the first week of length that are happening in the evening,
the great Canon of Saint Andrew of Crete,
that is a deep, deep engagement with the Old Testament.
And if you don't know the Old Testament,
a lot of this stuff is just gonna kind of fly by.
I'm sorry to say, that doesn't mean you should skip those services if you're not there yet.
Go and begin to have a kind of index for what you need to be working on.
So you know, as I said earlier, I'm going to say again, one of the most important themes
of this show, and I don't mean just this episode, I mean, the Lord of Spears podcast, which
which we started in 2020.
and we're barreling on down towards, you know,
or completing four years.
One of the most important things is that
this is all one scripture.
It's one faith, one Lord.
All of it is together.
And the more that you let that sink in,
I think the more that
your experience of our Lord Jesus Christ.
the more that your faithfulness will increase all of these things, I think, will become
vivified. And therefore, enable us to be living the way that we're supposed to live, to
live in faithfulness and repentance, not as a high-handed sinner that we read about in
numbers. Don't be that guy. You know, when you sin, put your hand down and say, okay,
I'm going to live differently now.
And not just don't sin, but do good,
because we are created for good works, as the Scripture says.
And part of the way we understand what those good works is,
is precisely in a deep engagement with what's in the Torah
and the rest of the Holy Scriptures.
Father Stephen,
I'll have to see you then.
So in my ongoing quest for cancellation, as I teased to that caller, let's talk about
the Jewish people.
How could this go wrong?
I've been I've been doing a lot with St. Paul lately, as I mentioned.
And the Jewish people were St. Paul's own people.
They're not my own people.
done the TMA.
I have no Jewish blood in me.
If that means something.
But St. Paul has this deep concern
on a number of levels.
And I think it develops over the course of his life.
It starts out as sorrow
that so many of his fellow Jewish people
haven't embraced Jesus as the Messiah.
And I think in the later epistles of St. Paul, it transforms into something that was even
more sorrowful for him because I think he saw at the beginning of something that unfolded
over the next few centuries, helped along by Roman violence, which was I think he saw the
movement surrounding Jesus, the church,
leaving the Jewish people behind.
What do I mean by that? Meaning the very earliest phase, not only was Christianity profoundly Jewish, it was a Judaism.
It was, it was, it was, it was, it was, it was as much claim to being Judaism as any other Judaism in the, in the first century AD.
the leadership the apostles were Jewish.
The main bodies of every church he planted
were Jewish.
people from the synagogue who embraced Jesus as the Messiah and then quote unquote convert because it wasn't a new religion
as well their Andrew just reminded us
But he saw more and more that
Gentile Christians Christians from the nations were coming in they were embracing Jesus as the Messiah and
And past a certain point is fellow Jewish people were not, at least not in the same
and not at the same rate. After his death, of course, the Romans destroyed Jerusalem.
They de-judified Judea. They cracked down.
Even the Patriarchate of Jerusalem, from 70 to 80 on, frankly, is a Gentile entity,
because it had to be, because the Jewish people, including Jewish Christian.
had all been expelled. And that certainly hasn't come back. In the first half we talked about
just some of the horrors and atrocities that came to Jewish people from outside over the centuries.
And I'm not going to do the thing where we infantilize the Jewish people and act like they're just
these pure innocent childlike victims of everyone else, that's not true either.
Plenty of Jewish people have done plenty of atrocities sometimes to their own people
Sometimes to other people that's continued to this very day let the listener understand so
That's not the issue
Some people will come and will say
Social media where this won't get them banned they will say well
Jews hate Jesus or Jews hate crime.
probably a lot of them do, so do a lot of atheists, so do a lot of pagans, so do a lot of other
people for various reasons. That doesn't mean we stop caring about those people, right?
That doesn't mean we write those people off or those people become irrelevant.
So what do we do in our present day within the Orthodoxy?
about the Jewish people, if we want to see Jewish people come and embrace Jesus as the Messiah
after all these years. And if we want, as I said I do, you know, if we dream of a day when
you know an actual Jewish patriarchate might be reconstituted because of the waves of Jewish people
accepting Jesus as the Messiah within the Orthodox Church, which would be a great and wonderful day.
Is there anything we can-
and due to help bring that about.
I am not going to suggest that what we need to do
is a bunch of proselytizing, meaning going and finding
Jewish people and trying to preach at them
and preach the gospel at them.
Not only has that happened a lot throughout the centuries
in some really dark ways, and when I say really
dark ways again, there may be some people get defensive
about that. But think of the
way, for example, that certain Protestant missionaries in Orthodox countries have treated Orthodox
people trying to proselytize.
When we're the ones on the receiving end of the proselytism, it feels a certain way.
And I would suggest that since it feels that way, we should not adapt those same procedures
toward other groups and other people.
But I am going to suggest is that it is very possible for us to try to go back to something
that was very much present in the early church.
And I don't just mean the first century in St. Paul, though St. Paul is a great example
of it.
The reality is Judaism and Christianity, like rabbinic Judaism and Christianity, were not really
two separate things until around 80.
500. I won't go into all that now, but I can back that up. Even when we're talking about
in the fifth century, they're not completely separate. And a concrete part of what that
means is that there was a conversation going on. There were people who knew each other
and shared social bonds. And the social bonds are the arena in which a lot of those conversations
were happening.
where people were talking about the Torah, the Hebrew Scriptures.
The part of the inheritance we have as Christians that is also part of the
cultural inheritance of the Jewish people, there's an overlap in that Venn diagram
it includes but is not limited to the Hebrew Scriptures, it includes but is not
limited to the Torah.
And that overlap presents a place for conversation, a place for discussion.
A place for trying to move people, not in a proselytizing way, but in an ongoing way of
seeking to understand the text and present and communicate that understanding and bring
more people to our understanding of the text.
So I say Paul always started in the synagogues.
Here we go to the teachers.
of the rabbis, and he would sit and he would discuss the Torah with them. He would talk
about interpretations and traditions of interpretation with them. Right? And a lot of them, he
didn't persuade, but some of them came to see what he saw and ended up becoming part of
the Christian movement. And so if we threw St. Paul and Attardis and we brought him to the
present day and he ran into a rabbi I guarantee you I know what he would do.
he would start talking about the Torah with him.
And he would try to say,
Jesus the Messiah has come,
and I know so because,
look here in the Torah.
That's what he would do.
And they would argue.
They'd argue a lot,
because that's how Jewish theology works.
Right?
But out of that argument
and those disagreements
that discussion things would happen.
So, if I'm saying,
I'm saying this is what we want to try to do.
store, how do we do that? Well, here's the step one. Step one, right, is we need some
Orthodox Christians who actually know the Torah. Who can actually speak that language.
And that's something we've left behind. That's something we're now unfamiliar with.
We can't have that discussion with Jewish people to try to show them the right way to read
the Torah that leads us to Jesus as the Messiah.
If we don't...
know the Torah and if we don't know how to have that discussion and we don't know how to reason from the Torah
so we need Christians who can do that. We need to prepare ourselves. Even if you're not going to be
right, I'm not suggesting every listener to this is going to put in years and be able to sit down with
a rabbi and talk about it right. Okay, I know, right. But everyone who's listening to this can get to the
point where they can have a constri-
conversation with a Jewish person who showed up at their parish.
You can get that far. It'll take some work. It'll take some time, but you could get there.
And some of us can work on that even more, and potentially do even more.
There's a big obstacle. And we'll be honest about this too.
Right most the more religious right a Jewish person is.
the less likely they are to be willing to talk to you as a Christian.
There's a lot of barriers.
There's a lot of reticence, right?
But the only thing you and I can do to try to break down that reticence
is to prepare ourselves to have the discussion,
to prepare ourselves to have that discussion in a constructive way, right?
This requires work on our part.
and everything father
Andrew said in his closing comments about all the benefits of us understanding the Torah, right?
You get all those too.
Even if you do what I'm suggesting and you never meet a Jewish person in your whole life,
you still will have gained all those things Father Andrew was talking about.
But maybe also if we do this, we can be part of the generation or the generation.
or the beginning of something that could result in something truly glorious.
The Jewish people turning and mass to their Messiah
to embracing a faith that really originally belonged to them.
That we share with them.
Jewish people like St. Paul came
and the early missionaries and the fathers came and shared the truth about God,
the truth about Christ with my ancestors. I think it's about time that we prepared
to do the same with those people's descendants.
Amen. Amen. That is our show for tonight. Thank you very much, everyone,
for this.
If you didn't happen to get through to us live this time around, we would still like to
hear from you.
You can email us at Lordofspirits at ancientfake.com.
You can message us at our Facebook page, where you can leave us a voice mill at speakpipe.com
slash Lordofspirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or need help finding a parish,
head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. specific.
There I was completely wasting out of work and down.
All inside it's so frustrating as I drift from town to town.
Yeah.
And if you are on Facebook, which,
I remind everybody, Father Stevens is not,
so you could try to call him out in the group and he won't appear.
You should be on Facebook, either, though.
If you are on Facebook, you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group.
You can leave reviews, ratings, all those places.
and share the show with a friend who's gonna benefit.
from it. Also, by the way, if you happen to be listening and it's still March 14th, you
can get Lord of Spirits the Book at 50% off just today only.
And finally, be sure to go to www.engstrafate.com.storksupport.com.
Help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air. Feel as though nobody cares
if I live or die, so I might as well begin to put some action in my life. You know what
it's called. Thank you, good night. God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000-
thousand times ten thousand and thousands of thousands,
seeing with a loud voice worthy as the land
that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12.